<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the 23. of Aprill, being the Lords day, called Sonday. 1581. By Anthonie Andreson</title>
            <author>Anderson, Anthony, d. 1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19291</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108525</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844183</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844183</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8972</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19291)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8972)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 165:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the 23. of Aprill, being the Lords day, called Sonday. 1581. By Anthonie Andreson</title>
                  <author>Anderson, Anthony, d. 1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[124] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [H. Bynneman? for] Ralph Nevvbery,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H(-H7-8).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8972:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8972:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON preached at Paules Croſſe, the 23. of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill, being the Lords day, called Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day. 1581.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Anthonie Andreſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Printed at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Ralph Nevv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery. Anno. 1581.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8972:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8972:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Eſquiers, maiſter Edmund Andreſon, Sergeaunt at Lawe to the <hi>Queenes moste excellent Maiestie: and</hi> to Maiſter <hi>Thomas Fanſhawe,</hi> hir Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Remembrauncer in hir honourable Court of Th exchequer, <hi>Anthony An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſon</hi> Miniſter of Gods holye Goſpell, ſendeth moſt Chriſtian ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it pleaſed god of his prouident purpoſe in his mercie to call mee (your poore kinſma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to that notable place and honourable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience at Paules Croſſe, to ſound forth the word of his Grace, whiche in the ſimplicitie of my ſoule, I carefullye there deliuered: So his wiſedome hath further vſed the godlye, and of good iudgement, (and not a fewe) to drawe from me my promiſſe, to profite hys people further abroad, by the ſame his holye worde in the office of this my
<pb facs="tcp:8972:3"/> willing pen: whiche laboure of mine therein, I haue (by the Lordes good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) now ſo faithfully here ſet down, as I ſuppoſe, neither anye Methode is altered, or matter omitted, that by me then was there ſpoken. Happily ſome other wordes in ſome places are vſed, (as otherwiſe it were not poſsible, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I ſhoulde haue firſte penned, and then conned my Sermon by hearte, whiche had bin a heauy laboure, bothe lothſome, &amp; needleſſe I praiſe God of his mercies, to whoſe glorie I ſpeak it) but the felf ſame ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of doctrine, matter, maner, and order, which both your worſhips with the reſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heard is here continued. If therefore it nowe ſeeme to obtaine leſſe, conſider the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is paſt, yet here is the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but wanting the voice, geſture, and perſon of hym that ſpake it: But no doubt Gods ſpirite ſhal open the harts of the Readers to receiue it (his ſeede) to their comfort, if they with deſire of gaine to their conſciences, turne ouer theſe little leaues. And I praie God,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:3"/> (in and by our Chriſte) that it maye fructifie as muche as my deſire is, and that is ſo much as poſsibly I can craue. And were it of much more valor (as it is for the handling, but in midle ſorte) no other choice woulde I make, than to bothe your Worſhippes (my good couſins) as to them, to whome I owe my ſelfe, for your louing and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all friendſhips towardes me. This my poore gifte, therefore accepte of your good natures, as from the heart of him that wiſheth you the whole treaſures of God, for euer to enrich you, in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſpirite, and ſoule, to eternall life: Whoſe defence be euer yours, and your for euer his, in Chriſte our Lorde, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your kinſman and wel-willer to his power in Chriſte, AN. ANDRESON.</signed> 
               <dateline>At my Chamber in London, <date>Iune. 6. 1581.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8972:4"/>
            <head>Emanuell. Let vs pray, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 13.6.</note>He ſpake alſo this Parable: A certaine man had a Figge tree planted in his Vineyard: And he came and ſought fruite thereon, and found none: then ſaid he to the dreſſer of his Vinyard: Behold, this three yeres haue I come &amp; ſought fruit of this Figge tree, and finde none: cut it downe: why kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth it alſo the ground barren? And he anſwered, &amp; ſaid vnto him, Lord, let it alone this yere alſo, till I digge rounde aboute it, and dung it: And if it beare fruite, wel: if not, then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thou ſhalt cutte it downe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ighte honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, learned, &amp; dearely beloued in our ſauioure Chriſte, this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred portion of Gods holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture thus read vnto you, is ſpoken by oure Maiſter
<pb facs="tcp:8972:4"/> Chriſt as a parable moſt fit, to expreſſe the wilful ignorance, and obſtinate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that pernitious people of <hi>Iewry</hi> which now, for their vnfruitefull hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and contemptuous reiecting of the greate graces offered them by the word of God, are in ſhorte time vtterly to bée caſte vnder the curſſe of Gods maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. The occaſion of this Parable, was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> carping ſpéeches of the <hi>Samarita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe Iewes,</hi> in cauſe of <hi>Pilates</hi> crueltye, againſt the <hi>Galileans,</hi> whoſe bloude hée had mingled with their pretenced ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, which abuſed the ſacrifices of right religion, in the moſt curſſed purpoſe, to open rebellion. whiche purpoſe being moſte vngodly, God vſed that ciuill po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, to méete with their attemptes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had begonne their indeuoure, althoughe in muche crueltie, the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent vſed right reuenge. The reporte whereof was brought to Chriſt, as ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by either to drawe from Chriſte ſome ſharpe cenſure of the Preſident his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell acte, or elſe to terrifie his ſacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in cauſe he taught, vnder ſo ſeuere a
<pb facs="tcp:8972:5"/> Ruler. But the Lorde ſawe their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie, and aunſwered them with greate diſcretion, affirming the execution of the ſinners to be iuſt, leauing the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of doing, to be decided before the Lorde, and by their owne tidings tooke happy occaſion to teach the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the doctrine of repentance, ſaying: <hi>Were theſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinners? I tel you nay: But except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi> And God himſelfe by that other kind of correction in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> dothe alſo fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne you, that not onely thoſe .xviij. vpon whome the Turret of <hi>Siloah</hi> fell, were ſinners, but alſo your ſelues yet left aliue, are likewiſe righte guiltie of death. And if you doe not by this his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie and extraordinarie hande, take occaſion to amend your liues: ye ſhall al likewiſe periſhe. But you are ſharpe of ſight into other mens actions, and moſt blinde to ſée your owne eſtate. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde: it is euen like to this Parable: <hi>A certaine man hadde a Figge tree, &amp;c.</hi> The Lorde hathe planted you <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> in his fruiteful lande, hée looketh
<pb facs="tcp:8972:5"/> for your holineſſe of lyfe to hym, hée laboureth to all that maye bee, that you ſhoulde be fruitefull, but often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, hée findeth you euer barren: Therefore it is not long ere you ſhall be cut downe, to your vtter confuſion. And thys was fulfilled by <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> aboute fortie yeares after the aſcention of our Sauiour Chriſte. And thus muche for the Iewiſh Figge tree.</p>
            <p>The argument or ſumme of thys Parable is, that manye are often ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered of GOD to remaine, whilſte ſome are weeded oute, that yet deſerue lyke caſtyng forthe, wyth others from the Vineyarde: And that this long ſuffering of oure good GOD, is to drawe vs to repentance, but if we (abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his grace) do remaine rebellious, our contumacie ſhall cauſe vs with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement force to be throwen from the Church and common weale of Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte, to the gaping gulfe of extreame hate, and perfecte miſery.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8972:6"/>
            <p>The partes of this Parable (in my iudgement) are two. Firſt here is ſette downe right notably the ſingular grace and goodneſſe of God to his people, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed here by this Figge trée. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the conſtrained ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence of Gods Iuſtice, to and vpon the ſame place and people, where before he hath notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding diffuſed his abundant grace.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The former parte is approued in theſe wordes: <hi>A certaine man hadde a Figge tree planted in his Vineyard, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond in theſe: <hi>Cut it down, why keepeth it the ground alſo barren, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great and ſingular goodneſſe of God ſhineth here moſt brightly, as wel in the baſeneſſe of the trée, whiche hée hath planted, as in the moſte excellente place, wherein he hathe right merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtabliſhed it. The <hi>Metaphor</hi> is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry elegante, taken from the Figge trée, which by nature in the roote is very bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, though by the Arte and labour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dreſſer, his fruit become right pleaſant to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eater. And ſurely, not only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of <hi>Iuda<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> but alſo of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> if they
<pb facs="tcp:8972:6"/> be pierced at the roote, ſhal approue this for moſte true, that they are naturallye bitter to the eye and pallate, of any ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible taſter. In birth we are moſte bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as being embrued from the concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with our firſte fathers ſin, and in bitterneſſe of ſin, (not by Marriage, but by naturall propagation) we are al con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued both King and Caitife. As <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> hathe ſaide: <hi>in ſinne hath my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conceiued me:</hi> For we are all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> and of one propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, after our common corruption. And in our birth no ſwéeteneſſe, but bitter grippings of the mother, bitter wraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of the child, and moſt bitter eſtate of the ſame, before the ſeconde byrth. Whereof I referre you to the reading of <hi>Ezech. 16.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech 16.1 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Chapter. Our father is an Amorite, our mother is an Hittite, our kindred is of curſſed Canaan, and wee polluted in our owne bloude, and by condition the children of Gods anger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.</note> Oh moſte bitter roote, and vnſauerie Figge trée. But are we bitter in oure life? happily ſome man woulde thinke,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:7"/> that reaſon might reache vs his hande of good direction. But (alas) we then waxe to encreaſe in bitterneſſe. For as the Wormewoode groweth bigger, and ſo increaſeth into bitterneſſe: euen ſo wée, as wée encreaſe in ſtature, ſtate and ſtrength, ſo do we abounde in bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of ſinne. And if we woulde more plainelye ſée thys, let eache man ſounde the ſea of hys hearte, and hée ſhall finde there, greate ſtony cragges ful of bitterneſſe and gall againſt God and his owne ſoule, and al godly men, albeit that Gods ſpirite of regeneration doth daily purge and mortifie the ſame. But from our ſelues lette vs caſte oure eies with truth into the earth, and into this our nation of <hi>England,</hi> and (o Lord) what bitterneſſe? what bitter contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies for religion receiued of the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie? what greate delight to drinke a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowſe of that Wormewoode water of Poperie,<note place="margin">Reuel. 7.11.</note> of which <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſpeaketh? And, as the thirde parte of the earth haue druncke of it, ſo they are become more than thrée parts bitter by
<pb facs="tcp:8972:7"/> it, againſte God, oure gratious Prince, hir godlye lawes, ſtate and people.</p>
            <p>What bitter hate beare they to the worde? howe bitterly bite they at the Preachers thereof? What bitter roote can yéelde ſuche iuice, as the Papiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſpirites doe ſtreame out againſte vs? Theſe are Figge trées indéede, planted in this holy lande, they make the ground barren and bitter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they dwell, their children, their ſeruaunts, their tenauntes, that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey that dothe entertaine them, thoſe friendes whiche doe accompany them, are eyther made verye bitter, vtterlye barren, or muche moleſted by them. The ſoyle of the lande they doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure, the Nurſſe of the Countrey (oure Gratious <hi>ELIZABETH</hi>) they doe deſpiſe. They are as Mice in the Lords barne, they eate vp the owners corne, but they refuſe to ioye his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. This bitter trée bringeth his fruite, but it is without the dreſſer of the Vineyarde: Euen ſuche as the <hi>Galileans</hi> broughte agaynſte theyr
<pb facs="tcp:8972:8"/> allotted Prince: ſeditions, conſpiracies, and publique rebellion. And whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer good oure godlye Nurſſe and good Princeſſe, doth endeuour, the ſame our bitter Papiſts turne to Wormewoode, reporting euil of godly lawes, and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp ſuch forraine foes, and domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call enimies, as they can procure to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay their beſte againſte vs. And theyr pretence, with the <hi>Galileans</hi> is religion, fréedome from the bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage of conſcience, and tyranny of now gouernement, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the moſt bound of them, reape much more fréedome, than either their cauſe, or conſcience can deſerue, or yet ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> win them thankeful vnto God. But is your Figge trée nowe readie ripe, you Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts? Your buds were preately broken in the North, hapely your after growth is bloſſomed nowe, and braggeth of his ripeneſſe, and your <hi>Louanistes, Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and late vpſtarte <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> are ready to reape the fruite of your bitter Figge trées. But (o Lorde) it is a bitter fruite, a peſtilent Figge, and a deadlye dyet, whiche they deſire, therefore graunte,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:8"/> that they may periſhe. They are (O Lord) rotten in their ripeneſſe, let them fall to confuſion, which in this merciful time of ſo much proyning and dreſſing, by thy holye worde, and hir Maieſties ſoftened ſworde, can not be conuerted vnto thée. But do you deſire a daye you bitter Papiſtes? What haue you to do with that daye? our ſinnes indéede doe fight againſte vs, and if our demerites bring vs a heauye daye, yet it is not yours, but the Lordes day. We may ſay to you, as the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 5.18</note> ſaide to his wicked ones in his time. <hi>What haue you to doe with the daye of the Lorde? woe to you that deſire it. The day of the Lord is darkeneſſe, and not light: it is as if a man didde flee from a Lion, and a Beare met him, or went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe, and leaned vpon the wal, and a Serpent bit him:</hi> So you runne from hir Maieſtie, ſuppoſing hir a Lion you Papiſtes, and hope after a day, but euen in that day, you (I ſay) ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured of the Bull, of Romiſhe <hi>Baſhan,</hi> &amp; the ſhe Beare robbed of hir whelpes,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:9"/> ſhall teare you in péeces. But you haue peace offred you, and you ſéeke for war. Wherefore you hunger your owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,<note place="margin">Ier. 24.</note> euen in that daye, wherein your ſuppoſe is of Popiſhe ſolace. But (beloued) were it that only the Papiſts of <hi>Englande</hi> were bitter, wée mighte in ſwéeteneſſe lament that ſoure fruite. But our ſelues are bitterly ſette one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte an other, our hearts and acts at home, our Courtes and Aſſiſes in the Countrey, oure thruſting and ruſhing into <hi>Westminster Hall,</hi> dothe compell you my Lordes of the Benches to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it, that <hi>Englande</hi> is full of bitter Figge trées. The Lorde be mercifull to chooſe vs into his vineyarde, louing to plante vs, willing to dreſſe vs, and to proine vs, that we may be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and bring forth by his operation, ſwéete Figges, and odoriferous fruites vnto him, for his holy names ſake. It maye yrke vs thus to heare of our bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe, but it may ſhame vs to féede of ſuche fruite. Surely it wearyeth one to thinke therof, and therefore I wil now
<pb facs="tcp:8972:9"/> recorde Gods mercie and goodneſſe to this Figge trée: namely, how he hathe planted it in his holy Vineyard. What he hathe there planted you haue hearde, euen a bitter Figge trée: Nowe, where it is planted, our Texte doth ſay, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in his Vineyarde, let euerye manne therfore apply this to himſelf, as it may appertaine him. The whole Realme of <hi>Englande</hi> is this Figge trée, planted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vniuerſall Churche of God. This Citie of <hi>London</hi> is likewiſe a parte of this Fig trée, growing out of the ſame. And euery Countrey, Towne, village, Potentate, preacher and priuate perſon is a braunch of this Figge trée of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande,</hi> being borne or nowe nouriſhed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. And ſo euery man is to apply this vnto himſelfe, that he is this Figge trée, planted in this land by Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, whych land, is of hys infinite grace and goodneſſe grafted into his Catholike Vineyarde, the vniuerſall holy Church of Chriſt Militant in earth. The fertili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this Vineyarde is ſuche, if thou do reſpect but the ſoile of the land, that wée
<pb facs="tcp:8972:10"/> muſte of neceſſitie ſay of it, that whych <hi>Eſay</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 5.2.</note> ſaide of <hi>Hieruſalem: <hi>My beloued had a Vineyarde in a very fruiteful hil:</hi>
               </hi> Of thys landes fruitefulneſſe I reſte to ſpeake in this noble Auditorie, leaſte I ſhoulde ſéeme to tell them, that by far greater experience may teache me, that it is the treaſure houſe of Gods abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant and fruitful bleſſings, ſeruing vs plentifully, and ſending hence abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſufficient proofe thereof to all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not only neare, but farre off ſituate from vs, Gods holy name be praiſed for it, &amp; Chriſt Ieſus make vs thankful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; fruitful Fig trées to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to hir Maieſty, &amp; truſty in truth, &amp; giue vs right Engliſh harts one to an other. Oh Lord how greate is thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? but herein muche more, namely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of thy infinite goodnes &amp; grace thou haſt placed vs in this fruitful land, &amp; planted the ſame, into thy moſt holy Vinyard, &amp; ſacred ſea of thy holy Churche. <hi>Engl.</hi> is a member of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of God, &amp; (thankes be to God) the church of God is in <hi>Engl.</hi> But here ſome Papiſt ſéemeth to ſaye,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:10"/> (me thinke) Nay ſir, not ſo, <hi>England</hi> is not, nor hathe the Churche of God in it. To whoſe blaſphemy we maye boldely anſwere: The perfect notes, &amp; infallible markes of Gods Church, both of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible &amp; inuiſible Churche, are apparante with vs in our Church of <hi>England</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>is the Vineyard of the Lord whiche is the houſe of Iacob and the Church of God.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa 5.7.</note> The viſible Church of God we call here, that Catholike com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, which is diſperſed into ſundry pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, &amp; are by the word of God called into one ſociety and felowſhip, as Gods elect people in outwarde profeſſion of ſincere religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, participate togither of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes Sacraments, make co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word, &amp; do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> publique &amp; priuate diſcipline of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, in ſéeming ſinceritie. And this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike &amp; militante company, are placed into ſundry territories, which for theyr ſituations &amp; diuerſitie of Countries, bée alſo deuided into particular Churches, and beare ſuch names, as the Country ſoile is knowen by, as the Church of <hi>Corinth, Laodicea, Epheſus, Theſſalonica,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:11"/> Englande, Fraunce</hi> and <hi>Irelande,</hi> &amp;c. And this viſible Churche as it hath in it in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Countrey where it is, bothe good and euil ones, elect and reprobate, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and infidelious,<note place="margin">Math. 3.22 Math 13.27 2 Tim. 2.20</note> holy and hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, Wheate and Cockle, Corne and Chaffe, veſſels of honoure and diſhes of diſgrace: So the ſaide Church of God, called the Militaunt Congregation, is knowne to be there, whereſoeuer theſe certaine notes and markes thereof are reſident,<note place="margin">The infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible markes of the iſible Churche of God.</note> and to be ſéene in common vſe: that is to ſay, <hi>Puritie of Doctrine, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere deliuerye of Chriſtes holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and godly Diſcipline</hi> Whiche aſſured markes and notes to knowe his Churche by, our ſauiour Chriſte hathe couched into one ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Goſpell, vnder the commaunding commiſſion from his Maieſtie to his holy Apoſtles, in the Goſpell after Saint <hi>Mathewe</hi> thus.<note place="margin">Math. 28.18</note> 
               <hi>And thus ſpake to his Diſciples ſaying: All power is giuen vnto mee in heauen, and in earth, go therefore &amp; teach al nations, baptizing them in the name of the father, and of the ſonne, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:8972:11"/> of the holy Ghoſte, teaching them to obſerue all thinges whatſoeuer I haue commaunded you, and loe, I am with you alwaye vntil the end of the world Amen</hi> In this ſacred ſentence (dearely beloued) are theſe thrée heauenly notes giuen of God, to trye if his Militante Churche be in whatſoeuer kingdome, Countrey or people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goe teache the Goſpell,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> this is the firſt: For whereſoeuer the doctrine of the word, is purely, after Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements delyuered and taughte, there is the Church of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is the true adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hys holy Sacraments, <hi>Baptizing them in the name of the father, &amp;c.</hi> Note wel, that not onely hys matter of Sacrament, but his methode in Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing muſt be obſerued, where his Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is eſtabliſhed, &amp; therfore the Lorde deliuereth both the matter, what, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manner, howe, ſaying: <hi>Baptize them</hi> thus: <hi>In the name of the Father and of the Sonne, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The thirde ſacred marke of this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb facs="tcp:8972:12"/> Churche, is regiſtred vnder theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: <hi>Teaching them to obſerue al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, whatſoeuer I haue commaunded you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 1.29</note> Do not (ſaieth the Lorde) onelye teache the nations my worde, but bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize the beléeuing, and thoſe whiche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue and are baptized, ſée that they bée kepte in my obedience, and vnder my ſwéete and eaſie yoke, by your aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in my ſpirite, that their conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amongeſt men, may aduaunce theyr confeſſion vnto God. Loe, here is the rule and warrant for godlye diſcipline in the Church of God. <hi>Teache them to obſerue,</hi> bring them to obey, directe the Segniorie into their duetye, teache them how they ought to gouerne in the Church: and let them exerciſe theyr au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthoritie to my glorie, and to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainaunce of the ſame. Whych then is in the right order, when they are taught by doctrine and diſcipline,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 1. Theſ. 4.2</note> to obſerue all and euery thing that I giue you in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement for them: and when you feare to preſſe vppon them, anye thing that you haue not receiued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:8972:12"/> might tie their conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to obſerue, as if it were of mine. Now this happy land of <hi>England,</hi> by Gods great mercy, hath al and euery of theſe marks, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God moſt purely taught, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Chriſt (in ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) ſincerely adminiſtred, &amp; godly diſcipline by wholeſome lawes eſtabliſhed: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Churche of <hi>England</hi> is the true church of God. For the firſt, we dare ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to the throne of God, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of vpright lerned men, that we haue the trueth of Gods holye doctrine taught amongeſt vs. Whiche doctrine alſo, by hir gratious Maieſtie, in hir godly laws is mightily maintained and by the helping hande of ſuch as be godly Magiſtrates, is greatly furthered, but by the learned fathers and zealous god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preachexs, moſt truly, diligently, and plainly in theſe our days deliuered. And we may for our doctrine in <hi>Eng.</hi> (appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as I haue ſaid) right boldly affirm, as <hi>Pet.</hi> the Apoſtle in his time, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtolical doctrine, ſaid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.25.</note> 
               <hi>And this is the word which is preached amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt you.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8972:13"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Chriſts holy Church, which Churche knoweth no moe) we haue them (in ſubſtance) ſincerely by law eſtabliſhed, and by the godly Miniſters likewiſe to Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple adminiſtred, without addition or defalking too or fro the worde of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> For the Diſcipline of the Church we alſo haue it (thoughe in ſome weaker ſorte) than either the auctoritie of the worde ſeemeth (to me) to affoorde, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grauitie of the cauſe, in our peſtiferous time, doth require it: Yet it cannot bée ſaid, but we haue eſtabliſhed diſcipline, by hir graces godly laws, to this Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of <hi>Englande,</hi> and at thys laſte Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament (agaynſt the Papiſts) haue the ſame Chriſtianly augmented. God gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that our godly and reuerende Biſhops, Iudges, Eccleſiaſticall Commiſſioners and officers whych haue the authority, may, and would, ſo vſe thys aucthoritye they haue, that God myghte be wonne, (as it were) wyth theyr godly indeuor, to enlarge the heartes of higher auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye ouer vs in the Lorde by lawefull
<pb facs="tcp:8972:13"/> power, to yéelde vs further and more ſeuere diſcipline, to one and all in thys Churche of <hi>Englande.</hi> Lord for thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake graunt it to this thy holy viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Vineyarde of <hi>Englande</hi> we beſeeche thée. And in the meane ſpace (brethren) let vs be obedient to this we haue, and heartilye praiſe God for the ſame, and pray earneſtly with conioyned hearts, for a further, by hir Graces aucthoritie, and the ſtrict rule of hys holy worde. Theſe holy and ſufficient notes of hys viſible Church, we haue in our Engliſh Church at thys day (the Lord be praiſed for them, and contynue them wyth vs) and therefore agaynſte al your blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to God, your ſiniſter, but ſubtill ſuggeſtions to Princes and people (o ye poore Papiſts) we ſtand by proofe to bée the Figge trée, planted indeede in the moſte holy Vineyarde of the Lorde, and haue our Churche conſecrated a ſacred member of the Catholike Churche of God, viſible wyth the reſt of that Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tante troupe and companye of ſanctified men in the vniuerſall earth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8972:14"/>
            <p>And as for the other forged marks of Vniuerſalitie, and perſonall ſucceſſion, we count it ſufficient to haue the ſociety with ſuche the ſonnes of God, as haue their felowſhippe with the Sainctes of Chriſte,<note place="margin">1. Io. 11.2.3 4.</note> and haue learned to forſake <hi>the company of the wicked, and to auoide the way of ſinners,</hi> but greatly deteſte, to ſtoupe to that Cacolike <hi>Apoſtata</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 1.</note> whych ſo arrogantly ſetteth hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in that chaire of the ſcorner. But touching perſonall ſucceſſion of Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prickes and Churches, we holde it not to be always a ſure marke of Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Churche. Except ye wil ſaye of the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> vnder <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> that Idolatour, that ſhe was then the true Churche, (thoughe an <hi>Apoſtata</hi> by hir groſſe Idolatrie) bicauſe ſhe could boaſt of perſonall ſucceſſion from the Kyngs, and Biſhoppes of that people. Or that the Churche of <hi>Iudah</hi> vnder <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> (that idolatrous King) was (notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the murther of Gods chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, their ſacrificing to Idols, theyr ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing out of the lawe of the Lorde, and
<pb facs="tcp:8972:14"/> banyſhing hys holy ſacrifyces,) was (I ſaye) (all thys admitted) yet the true Church of God, bycauſe they hadde and coulde ſhewe a perſonall ſucceſſion of Kyngs and Byſhoppes, euen from the firſte <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> But yée wyll poſſibly preſſe vs wyth the auctoritie of the Fathers, as wyth <hi>Tertullian</hi> that ancient, whych boaſted in truth, to haue had ſucceſſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Byſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> for the furtheraunce of hys purpoſe. But forget not (you Papiſts) that as yet the Fathers of that Church had not depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the faith: but wyth theyr ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion had contynued the Apoſtolicall doctrine, vppon whiche point <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> chiefly ſtoode: as it may appeare by hym. And alſo, would God you would not wyth malitious heartes ſéeke to darken that notable doctrine of hys, in that hys Booke of preſcriptions, that althoughe manye Churches, haue not to ſhewe theyr perſonall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Byſhoppes, yet, if ſo they haue the Apoſtolicall doctrine,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:15"/> taught ſincerely in them, for that conſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinitie and kinred in Doctrine: thoſe Churches are, and are to be accompted Apoſtolicall. The Orientall Churches hadde due ſucceſſion til <hi>Arrius</hi> had infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted them with hys poyſon: ſhall perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſucceſſion nowe approue the ſect of the <hi>Arrians</hi> to be the church of God? So had the Churche of <hi>Rome</hi> before <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtes</hi> poſſeſſion therof. Shal we ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now ſay, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their doctrine, theyr malice, theyr ambition, theyr pride, theyr dyueliſhe conuerſation dothe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince them to be that whore of <hi>Babilon:</hi> Shal we (I ſay) now ſay, bycauſe they poſſibly can ſhew vs a great Catalogue of Byſhops from <hi>Linus</hi> or <hi>Anacletus,</hi> that therefore they are nowe the true Churche of God? And yet, were that a ſufficient proofe of Gods Churche, our Biſhops in <hi>England</hi> then haue their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall ſucceſſion from the firſte, euen the firſte that you can name, as by time, and nexte courſe ſuccéeding one an other.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſée (dearely beloued) howe apparant it is, that this noble Realme
<pb facs="tcp:8972:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> of <hi>Englande</hi> is planted by Gods greate mercy into the Catholike Vineyarde of the Lorde, the viſible Churche of God, and is it ſelfe a notable member of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now time requireth, that we ſpeake ſomething likewiſe of the inuiſible co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and Church of God, to the greater comforte of the godlye in thys viſible Churche, whiche this day heare me, or hereafter may heare of this holy labor, to their further benefite. If thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt knowe certainly (beloued) in thine owne conſcience, whether thou arte ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily and indéede, the member of Chriſt, and ſo a liuely braunche of the virident Vine, end a fruitful Figge trée: examine thy ſelfe by theſe thrée pointes,<note place="margin">The true notes of the inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church</note> al which the ſpirite of God againe hathe laide vp in one moſt ſacred Sentence, and thys it is: <hi>The end of the commandement is loue out of a pure hart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>and of a good conſcience, and of ſaith vnfained.</hi> In thys ſentence (beloued in Chriſt) is laid forth vnto vs, the verye true and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libe tokens to euery mans ſoule, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:8972:16"/> he be the ſonne of God or no. For, by degrées, from the fruite to the trée, from the childe to the parent, he goeth &amp; fetcheth thence vnto vs, the certaine markes, whereby we are ſealed to the Lorde. The purpoſe of God, giuyng his worde, is (ſaith the Apoſtle) that yée purely loue one another, but your loue muſte procéede from a good conſcience, not from a corrupted hart, and this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience hath his purging from an vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned faith. Then take hence your cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine notes of Gods children, and theſe they are. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, by the vertue of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and word of God, a pure faith vnfai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, a renued minde, whiche here is called a pure heart. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And thirde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the ſame ſpirite, ſuche charitie, as neither can be cold or hypocriticall. In whom ſoeuer theſe be vigent &amp; warme, let him be aſſured, though al the Popes in <hi>Rome</hi> had ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t their curſes againſt him &amp; this honorable natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet he is of god, the member of Chriſt, &amp; one of his inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Churche, whyche can not be caſte forth of the dores.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8972:16"/>
            <p>But that we maye the better knowe howe to ſounde our heartes, and haue a more ful féeling of this heauenly ſwéet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, let vs learn what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> operation of this vnfained faith required. Surely, it worketh by Gods ſpirit and word thrée notable things in vs.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, a perfect beléefe in our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, that though our outwarde ſhoulde be fully puniſhed for ſinne, yet our inwarde man, ſhoulde haue prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue to bring both to the fauor of God bicauſe our ſinnes are not laide to oure charge,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.7.8 Pſ. 32.1 1. Io. 1.</note> but remitted fully in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging bloude of Ieſus Chriſt. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore through his merite (our faith appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending him) we may approche by that newe and liuing way, vnto his grace,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.19.</note> and call vnto him, as his iuſtified chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <hi>Abba, <hi>deare Father,</hi>
               </hi> and reſte aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that we, by pure faith vnfained haue Chriſte Ieſus to be to vs againſte our ſinful folly, Gods holy wiſdome, our iniquity, Gods righteouſnes, our groſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, his holineſſe, &amp; againſt our dailye &amp; deadly ſins: Chriſt Ieſus our ſufficient
<pb facs="tcp:8972:17"/> raunſome,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.30.</note> as the Apoſtle hathe ſette it downe vnto vs in theſe words: <hi>But ye are of him in Chriſt Ieſus, who of God is made vnto vs, wiſedome and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and ſanctification, &amp; redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſeconde worke of this our vnfained fayth, is growing from the firſte, to aſſure our heartes of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of Gods fauour, and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of vs in hys loue for euer and euer, ſo as, neither our dayly ſinnes, or Sathans accuſations, or yet the verye Iuſtice of God can poſſibly take hys fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue from vs, or impeache our great fauour with him, or by laying to our charge true thynges agaynſte vs, could yet caſt off hys ſingular loue from vs,<note place="margin">Rom. 8. tot. cap.</note> of al whych, that moſte noble chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of bleſſed <hi>Paule,</hi> the eyghte to the <hi>Romaines</hi> doth aſſure vs. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſte of all, thys faith is ſo renued by the worde of God, that it can not but ſaye, to mans ſoule that hath it, <hi>Bleſſed art thou whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che haſte thy parte in the firſte reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 2.6</note> 
               <hi>for thou ſhalte not taſte of the ſecond death, but ſhalt be the Prieſt of
<pb facs="tcp:8972:17"/> God, to raigne with hym a thouſande yeares.</hi> But will yée knowe (beloued) who hath this regenerating faith? veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, euen onely they, which are of a pure hart: For this is the ordinary worke of God, by faith firſt to approch vs to his holy preſence, to make vs his beſte belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued children, to iuſtifie vs by his grace, and to ſanctifie vs by his ſpirite. Then the ſame ſpirite deſcendeth to the ſecond degrée of his moſt holy labor,<note place="margin">Ezech. 36. Ephe. 4. Coloſſ. 3.1.</note> and dothe with his moſte holye finger, forme and frame vs anewe, changeth our acts and hearts, and faſhioneth vs, to the Image of God, in true holineſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And out of all doubte, greate is the glorious God, by whoſe mighty ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the ſea of mans hearte is turned ſo quite to another courſe ſo as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite he is brought to hate that horrible vice, whiche before he honored, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to loue, and embrace with great delight that vertue whiche before he did deſpiſe. And to deſire, to do thoſe bleſſed things, of whyche he earſt could take no pleaſure. And this is that puritye of the
<pb facs="tcp:8972:18"/> hearte by the Apoſtle to <hi>Timothie</hi> ſo greatly commended, and is the ſeconde ſound note of Gods holy childe and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the inuiſible elect and predeſtinat Churche, to life euerlaſting. And thys ſeconde note you ſée conſiſteth in theſe thrée bleſſed vertues. <hi>The true hate to ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. Pſ. 119.</note> 
               <hi>euen as to a Serpent. The ſincere loue of righteouſneſſe, with the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the whole body and ſpirit to it. And thirdly, the inwarde deſire of the heart in ſoule and body, to doe the wil of God:</hi> Althoughe the ſame godly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire by mightie battels with ſinne, and Sathan, is euery day impugned: as by <hi>Paule</hi> in the ſeauenth of the <hi>Romaines,</hi> is moſte notably ſette downe, whether for breuities ſake I ſende thée. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The laſte note of the inuiſible Church, and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of it, is ſincere loue &amp; burning chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, loue or vncorrupted charitie, which procéedeth from true faith, is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with aſſured hope, diffuſed by the ſpirite of God into vs, and ſo borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our brethren, as we ſhunne by euill example to hurte them, and take greate
<pb facs="tcp:8972:18"/> care with all our power,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10 31</note> to doe them benefite, euen as the Lorde hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs, and doe omitte the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of reuenge, or hatefull me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of euil done déedes: But, as God for Chriſtes ſake, hathe forgiuen vs, doe from the botome of our harts, forgiue and forget the iniuries of oure brethren, according to this ſaying of Gods ſpirite by <hi>Paule:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph, 4 31.32.</note> 
               <hi>Lette al bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and anger, and wrath and euill ſpeaking, bee putte awaye from you, wyth all malitiouſneſſe. Bee yee curteous one to another, and tender hearted, forgiuing one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, euen as God for Chriſtes ſake forgaue you.</hi> Shall wée putte the Papiſtes to ſilence (o ye bleſſed people?) In this then doe it, that they blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming vs as euil doers, may haue their mouthes ſtopped by our godlyneſſe of life.</p>
            <p>And further,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.12.15.</note> that ſo we maye make our calling ſure, and an entring into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euerlaſting Kingdome of God. Nowe then apply thys doctrine to your ſelues,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1 10.11.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:8972:19"/> (deare brethren) that yée haue nowe hearde, and ſaye to your hearts, for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte (if ye finde in trueth theſe markes liuely in you.) Now we know for truth that Gods ſpirite dothe aſſure our ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> that we are the ſons of God. And ſo maye you be bolde, to bleſſe God for thys grace, and ſay vnto the Papiſtes, Gods goodneſſe is great, who hath plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs in <hi>Englande,</hi> and <hi>Englande</hi> into his Catholike Vineyarde, both viſible &amp; inuiſible. But beholde, yet further, his gracious goodneſſe appeareth, &amp; is right notable to behold. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For in this Vineyard of his holye Churche of <hi>Englande</hi> to the great benefite of the Figge trée he hathe firſte placed <hi>a watche Tower.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 5.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> He hath ſecondly ſet <hi>a Hedge of defence</hi> rounde aboute it. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And thirdly, hauing ſtoned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grounde, hée hathe ſtabliſhed <hi>a Wine preſſe within the yarde,</hi> where eache trées fruite, ſhall, in conuenient time be brought to his tryall &amp; purpoſe of bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. If that noble Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> could ſay ſo of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> maye not Gods Prophets crye it out nowe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="tcp:8972:19"/> 
               <hi>Englande,</hi> and ſay, the Lordes goodneſſe is maruellous greate to thée (o thou Figge trée of <hi>England</hi>) For he hath placed thée in hys owne Vineyarde, he hath ſet vp a <hi>Turret</hi> in thée, whence thy watche men may ſée thée, and thyne enimies purpoſe agaynſte thée, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hence to giue thée warning of thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended harmes. And he hathe ſette hys hedge of prouidence rounde about thée, in more ample wiſe than euer had the <hi>Iſralits,</hi> for they had but warrant, when they came vp to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to worſhip, that no enimies ſhoulde inuade them. But thou <hi>England</hi> arte and haſte béene hedged and defended, by the Lords mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, not ſéeking to ſerue God, but after a faſhion waxing colde of hys ſeruice, and haſte giuen thy ſelfe to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and ſecuritie in ſinne, arte called, and goeſt rather backwarde: And yet, thine enimies abroad,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11 1. Eſa. 7.1.2. &amp; deinceps</note> and thy falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates at home, ſéeking to make a breache in thée, thy God, <hi>Englande,</hi> thy good God, ſaith, it ſhall not be, and hath vpholden thée, and defended thée, by him
<pb facs="tcp:8972:20"/> ſelf againſt al ſecrete conſpiracies open rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; forrain threats, now full this <hi>22.</hi> yeres. Thy name be bleſſed for it, my God, &amp; Lord, giue our <hi>Englande</hi> eies, to ſée hir ſins, &amp; thy long ſuffring ſafetie to vs &amp; for vs in this thy prouident hedge. The pollicie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> watchers, whereof hir Maieſtie is chiefe, (whom the Lord ſtill defend ouer vs, that long ſhe may wake to God, and watche godlily, for this hir people of <hi>England,</hi> and alſo the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical, and ciuil honorable councel, and Chriſtian gouernors) is great no doubt, for whoſe great and godly paines to vs, we owe in truth greate things to them, and manye bleſſings to God. Yet is it neither ſimply, hir Maieſtie, their polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, or other indeuor. (For al theſe with vs are ſinners, in his ſight) but hys ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hande alone, and that for his owne names ſake, that hitherto hathe guyded their holy counſels, and defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vs. Oh that the watchemen of oure <hi>Englande,</hi> would conſider then right déepely theyr place. You be ſet my Lords alofte, to ſee aloofe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> help of vs that are appointed
<pb facs="tcp:8972:20"/> vnder you. Your carcks &amp; care may not be, the Biſhop to become very rich, the Iudge to be of great reuerence, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor &amp; ruler, to gape after priuat gaine, but you muſte be all helping, rather vs, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſelues, yea, to your own loſſe, in winter, ſommer, heat &amp; cold, day and night my Lords, euen as hiding places from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> winde, a refuge for the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt, as riuers of water, in a thirſtie place, &amp; as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhadows of greate rockes, in a wearye land. So the Lord hath allotted you.<note place="margin">Eſa. 32.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> So <hi>Eſay</hi> the Prophet hath told you. And the reuerend Biſhops muſt lerne to know, that God hath called the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſuch reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d places, that they ſhoulde not be more y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and Lordly,<note place="margin">Acts. 20.</note> but more labouring and lowely, yea, if poſſible it may be, than their inferior brethren called to like fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the Lord, and holy office of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. And (beloued brethren) of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular ſorte, our partes is to bleſſe God, for our godly gouernors, both reuerende fathers, and the ciuil Magiſtrates, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che doe manye of them painefully tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile in their places to watche ouer vs.
<pb facs="tcp:8972:21"/> And are to pray wyth ſighs and ſobbes to God, for ſome ſuche of them, as ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther teache as they ought, or watche as they ſhoulde, or yet procure ſuch as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly would to the benefite of the Fig trée. I knowe ſome where, ſome places in <hi>England,</hi> that haue a Turret or Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, but no Preacher in it almoſte ſince hir Maieſties raigne: For why? the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall officers looke ouer it, ſome tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſtatute, and ſtearne Papiſtes, doe ſo out-countenaunce it, as, neither the worde is deſired, or can with quietnes happily haue grace of hearing. The lord from heauen be mercifull vnto hys peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in earth. Wel we muſt render to either ſtate, our due obedience, ſuffer them to ſtone vs, wéede vs, &amp; proine vs, that we may become fruitefull, and ſo behaue our ſelues in al thinges by loue towardes them, that as they muſt ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der accompts to God, for theyr offyces, ſo they maye take pleaſure to exerciſe theyr function amongſt vs. So doth the holye Apoſtle teache vs,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> ſaying: <hi>Obey them that haue the ouer-ſight of you,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:21"/> and ſubmit your ſelues: for they watch for your ſoules, as they that muſt giue accomptes (to God) that they may do it with ioy, and not with grief for that is vnprofitable for you.</hi> The Lord fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, he ſtoned his Vineyarde, and ſurely he hath mightily by hir Maieſty, cropped the toppes, and caſte out of the Churche of <hi>Englande,</hi> the ſtony hearted Papiſts. It remaineth, that the ſtoners vnder hir grace, be not ſtony the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: For, if they be Papiſticall, that be Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, howe ſhal the Papiſtes of <hi>England,</hi> be ſtoned out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Vineyard? Lord, thou clenſing God, preſerue thy little church of <hi>Englande,</hi> clenſe the Benches of the lande, that Benchers maye call to the barre, ſuch as hinder the growth of the Fig trée, in euery part of this thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom &amp; by iuſtice, authoritie &amp; grace, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert them Lord, or caſt them out of thy Vineyarde: For why Lorde, ſhoulde they alſo make the ground barren? The allegory of the Wine preſſe, lette it be thus vnderſtoode, the worke offered of God to euery calling in this hys Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde
<pb facs="tcp:8972:22"/> of <hi>Englande.</hi> The noble Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates haue vs hir people committed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, the Lorde doth looke, that their indeuour ſhoulde fill the preſſe with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly labors. The reuerende Fathers, and learned Preachers of the lande, haue their people: namely, the Church of God to exerciſe themſelues vpon. The graue Iudges haue their gréedye plaintiffes and defendants, to trye their induſtrie, and toyling ſeruice, yet holy to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde. And ſurely my Lordes, you muſt ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and with good courage tread y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Wine preſſe in your Aſſiſes, and in <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Hall.</hi> Your calling doth not onelye teache it you, but your verye robes doe preache it vnto vs: You ſitte in bloudye Gownes of Scarlet hewe, as whereby your very apparell dothe prognoſticate to your ſelues, and vs, with what hate to ſinne and zeale to God, you muſte ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the lawes, euen to the not only drawing of bloud, by the ſword of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but euen to the dying of the place with the bloud of the wicked, whiche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe can not be reclaimed. Your
<pb facs="tcp:8972:22"/> eyes muſte not looke vppon the mightie againſte the pore, or ſpare to ſtrike the ſtrong, that elſe would grinde the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnto powder: But you muſte aboue all (my Lordes) that be Iudges, take greate care of religion, and if in your circuites, you happily find any one ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, that wil not acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippes to the hearing of the worde, the ſame you muſte call to barre to taſte of the ſworde: For the iudgement is the Lords and not mans. O Lorde that I might once ſée that example in <hi>England,</hi> of ſome one godly Iudge or other, that, if any his aſſociates refuſed in conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte of the word and lawes eſtabliſhed to go with him to Churche, to heare the word of God there preached, his Lord would commaund him from the Bench to the Barre, yea, though he were a Lorde. Some of you my Lords are more gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beholding vnto God, as by health and ſickeneſſe, drawne nearer and nearer him, and are reſtored againe vnto life, that Chriſte Ieſus ſhoulde be ſéene
<pb facs="tcp:8972:23"/> afreſhe to liue in you. The Lorde doth knowe his Churche hath néede of you: and therefore in mercie he hath agayne lent vs you, play the men, and helpe to ſtamp into the Wine preſſe, thoſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che without you can not be broughte to tryall, and muche hinder the gratious growth of the Figge trée. Let your god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heartes, take that auncient precepte from <hi>Iehoſophat,</hi> that godly King, vnto you, which ſaith, or rather Gods ſpirite, in that place of the Chronicles:<note place="margin">2. Chro. 19.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>Take heede what yee do, for yee execute not the iudgementes of manne, but of the Lorde, and he wil bee with you in the cauſe and iudgements. Wherfore now let the feare of the Lord be vpon you: Take heede, and doe it: for there is no iniquitie with the Lorde our God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect of perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, nor receiuing of rewarde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Wine preſſe for you (my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) of the vulgare ſorte, is, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian duety, whiche of duty we owe one vnto an other, teaching vs to liue god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily,<note place="margin">Titus. 2 11. Gal. 6.9.</note> ſoberly, iuſtly, and not to be weary
<pb facs="tcp:8972:23"/> of wel doing one to another, but as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles alwayes light, we ſo ſhine,<note place="margin">Math 5.</note> that our workes may procure Gods praiſe. Let vs doe good vnto all menne, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to the Children of God. And know wel, that the Apoſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> teacheth this to be the end of our placing in the Vineyarde, that we be wel exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cized in the Wine preſſe, ſaying:<note place="margin">Eph. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>Wee are his workma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſhip created in Chriſt Ieſus vnto good workes whiche God hath ordayned, that we ſhould walke in them.</hi> And thus muche of the firſt part concerning the great goodneſſe and grace of God, to his Churche this adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Figge trée. And now (beloued) we approche to the reſte of our Texte, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſetteth ſorth vnto vs the ſharpe and ſeuere ſentence of God, vppon the ſame Figge trée, that was before ſo happilye harboured.</p>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:8972:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſeconde parte.</hi> Then, ſaide hee, to the Dreſſer of thys Vineyard, beholde, theſe three yeres haue I come and ſought fruit of this Figge tree, and finde none: Cutte it down, why kepeth it alſo the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d barren?</head>
               <p>THis ſecond parte of our text (deare brethren) containeth two ſpeciall points. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the Lordes long ſuffering the vnfruitfull Fig trée, to ſtand in hys Vineyard, wherein his great goodneſſe is yet further declared. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondely, hys heauy ſentence vpon the Fig trée, after the long abuſe of his greate patience. <hi>Then ſaid he to the dreſſer of his Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, beholde, theſe three yeres haue I come, &amp;c.</hi> Oh happy Vinyard that hath ſuch a Lord, who doth not only plant it, defend it, &amp; fructify it, but alſo doth daily viſite y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, calleth vpon his people, &amp; offereth them the remembraunce of the ende, wherefore they are ſo planted and placed in his holy Church. He commeth
<pb facs="tcp:8972:24"/> firſte in long patience, to his ſlouthfull trées to ſée, if at lengthe they can take bloſſome, and bring him fruite. Note then (good people) the ende of your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, it is to be holy,<note place="margin">Heb. 3.13.</note> liuely workers in the Lordes Vineyarde,<note place="margin">Iude. verſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 20.21.22.23 Eſa. 58.</note> to laboure the Lords increaſe, by teaching &amp; exhorting one an other, while it is to day, helping vppe ſome, and pulling out other from the fire, comforting the weake, walking with the ſtrong, deliuering the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſetting the priſoners frée, reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring eche man hys right, vſing no vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to the litle flocke, but by godly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in life, and daily practiſe to their good, ſo to yéelde our Figges to our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that they ſéeing our good workes, maye glorifie our Father whyche is in Heauen.<note place="margin">Math. 5.16.</note> And thus ſhall we make oure calling and election ſure, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> hath taught vs, ſaying: <hi>Giue al diligence thereto, to bee partakers of the godlye nature, ſleeing corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and luſte, ioyne moreouer ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue wyth youre fayth, and wyth Vertue, Knowledge, and wyth
<pb facs="tcp:8972:25"/> knowledge, temperance, and with te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraunce patience, and with patience godlineſſe, and with godlineſſe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly kindeneſſe, and with brotherlye kindeneſſe, loue. For if theſe things be among you, and abounde, they will make you, that yee neyther ſhall bee ydle nor vnfruiteful in the knowledge of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte.</hi> The Lords people muſte doe the Lordes workes, &amp; the working God doth require a labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring people. Forget not (beloued) that the Lorde of this Vineyarde doth in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting vs often ſéeke for fruite. Thrée thinges are of this Texte to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſte, hée commeth not haſtily, to looke if the trée be full of fruit, (although his ſoule deſireth the firſte ripe fruites) but he louingly looketh as a manne deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of ſome, and if the trée be very ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, he doth not ſpéedely depart, as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry at the ſame: but he taketh the bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghes tendrely into his holy handes, and he lifteth vp the leaues therof, and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth diligently, if ſo there be any one Figge there, once, twice, and thrice, and
<pb facs="tcp:8972:25"/> verye often, and if he at anye time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, find but ſome fruit, be it but here and there a Figge, he yet kéepeth a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing for that trée. But if after ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and paineful ſearching, he yet (from whome nothing can be hidde) can finde no fruite, then pronounceth he his curſſe, vpon that Figge trée, and ſaieth: <hi>Cut it down, &amp;c</hi> Oh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> long loking eies of Gods mercie vpon the Figge trées of <hi>Englande:</hi> He came vnto them in the beginning of hir Maieſties raigne, and did mercifully plant vs, he hath daylye ſince come by his Prophets ordinary &amp; extraordinary, and all to trimme and proine vs,<note place="margin">Io. 15.</note> that we abiding in his Chriſt might bring forth more fruite. But hée hath by his correcting hande to <hi>London,</hi> (oh <hi>London</hi> looke to it, thou City of God) and other places with puniſhing roddes of plagues and ſodaine deathes, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually of late viſited vs, as thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing our wantes of fruite. And now he ſtirreth vppe the courage of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets (the godly Preachers whiche tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare him) with one conſent to ſound,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:26"/> as it were the ſolempne blaſte of a laſte viſitation, that if we can not yet be fruitefull,<note place="margin">Eſay. 65.8.9.10.11.12.13.14.15.</note> they ſhoulde tell thée (O <hi>Englande</hi>) that then this hys Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde ſhall be taken from thée, and thou caſte out of it, and ſhalt ſée it gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to a nation that ſhall bring forth his expected fruite. Oh <hi>Englande,</hi> GOD make thée carefull and minde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of this ſeuere ſentence, <hi>Cutte it downe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, let vs here note, how the Lorde ſaith not, I haue come and found no Bloſſomes, but <hi>I haue come and founde no fruite.</hi> Fruite, and apte fruit (beloued) is that whych the Maiſter of the Vineyard expecteth. Bloſſomes are blowne awaye with a blaſte, Buddes are beaten downe with ſtormye tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtes, but ſwéete fruite is moſte méete for the Lordes mouthe. But it is a harde thing for the bitter Figge trée to alter hys nature: Wherefore he often draweth the vigoure of the earth to féede his bitterneſſe. Looke vppon the Iewiſhe Figge trée, and
<pb facs="tcp:8972:26"/> the Lord comming after long expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for good fruite, what fruites founde he? <hi>Eſay</hi> ſayeth:<note place="margin">Eſay. 5.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee looked that it ſhoulde bryng foorthe Grapes, but it broughte foorthe Wilde Grapes, viz. hee looked for iudgement, but beholde oppreſsion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ 8.</note> 
                  <hi>for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but beholde, a crying of them that are oppreſſed, throughe ioyning of houſe to houſe,</hi> and fielde to fielde, ſo as they woulde baniſhe the poore, to dwell alone by themſelues.<note place="margin">11.</note> Earely vp to dronkenneſſe and bibbing from morning till nighte, banquetting, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, piping and dauncing, but no regarde of the worke of the Lorde, wherefor he hathe made them. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore,<note place="margin">Verſ. 20.</note> they gaue a contrary tongue vnto God: For they yéelded commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of that whiche was noughte, and flatly condemned the ſimple good. They altered the tymes and ſeaſons to their owne fantaſies, darkeneſſe for light, bitter for ſweete, and ſwéet for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.<note place="margin">21.</note> They eſtéemed mannes pollicie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Gods diuinitie, makyng muche
<pb facs="tcp:8972:27"/> of their owne conceits, and became pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in their owne ſight, they durſt vſe, and bragge of it, that a carowſing Cup, or a harty draught coulde not ouertum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them, &amp; therefore they woulde ioine <hi>Bacchus</hi> to <hi>Venus</hi> ſtill.<note place="margin">Verſ 23.</note> Finally, they abuſed the ſeate of Iuſtice, Equity was ſent from home, and the wicked were iuſtified for bribes, yea, the godly, and his cauſe was by the aduerſe power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepted of his right, and hys caſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, ſo as either the righteouſneſſe of his cauſe was darkened, or much dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, or the true alowance to it vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken away: therefore the Lorde did threaten his cutting down,<note place="margin">Eſay. 5.24.</note> ſaying: <hi>Like as the flame of fire deuoureth the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, and as the Chaffe is conſumed of the flame: So their roote ſhall bee as rottenneſſe, and their bud ſhall ryſe vp like duſte, bycauſe they haue caſte off the lawe of the Lorde of hoſtes, and contemned the worde of the holy one of <hi>Iſraell.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> But nowe let vs looke into the long ſuffering of this our God to this people.
<pb facs="tcp:8972:27"/> 
                  <hi>Beholde, (ſaith he) theſe three yeares haue I ſought for fruit and finde none.</hi> By this terme of time, we are to note (beloued) the long ſuffering of God, which calleth by it to repentance. So he dealt with the world in the dayes of the floude, yea, euen when he was ready to ſtrike, then he gaue them afreſhe a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger time to repent, namely, <hi>20.</hi> yeres.<note place="margin">Gen. 6.3.</note> So prolonged he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of his plagues, to their poſteritie, euen when the daye was conceyued, to ſée if they would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent his anger with their returning vnto him. And by his holye Prophets, cryed vnto them: (oh ye people) why wil you dye?<note place="margin">Ezech. 33.11</note> 
                  <hi>Turne you from your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil wayes: gather your ſelues togither</hi> (o people) not worthy to be beloued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the dreſſer come forth, and ye be as chaffe that paſſeth in a day, and before the fierce wrath of the Lorde come vpon you.<note place="margin">Zephany. 2.12.</note> But they greatly abuſed his great forbearing, and ſo do we. <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſaide of them,<note place="margin">Ierem. 25.3</note> that hée hadde called them to repentaunce ful <hi>23.</hi> yeares, earely and late, but they woulde not heare nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline
<pb facs="tcp:8972:28"/> thine eares to obey, but prouoked him to anger, albeit he long ſuffered them, and ſente to them his Prophets, as before is ſaide. Oh <hi>Ieremy</hi> (Gods holy Prophet) thy terme of time is caſt vppon vs. Theſe thrée and twentie yeares hathe the Lorde in mercye by the voice of his Prophetes, called for fruite of vs in <hi>Englande.</hi> But what ſhoulde be our fruites? Surely, a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple degrée in fruites, the Lorde dothe require of vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſte a generall fruite, as we be all profeſſed into our Chriſte. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And then a ſpeciall, namely, euery trée his owne fruite.<note place="margin">Philip. 1.27.</note> Of the firſte the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh thus: <hi>Let your conuerſation be as it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth the Goſpel of God, &amp;c.</hi> That is, that our heartes be one in iudgement, oure offections in loue, our confederacie in godlyneſſe, ſuche as wée ioyne hands in vnitie one with another, to fight togither through the faith of the Goſpell againſte the aduerſary, and not as diſmembred bodies and companies, to deuoure one an other by iarring
<pb facs="tcp:8972:28"/> braules and cauſeleſſe contentions. Let this (beloued) be neuer out of our minds which are of one religion: <hi>If ye bite one an other,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5 15.</note> 
                  <hi>take heede leaſte ye be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed one of an other.</hi> Our vnitie &amp; loue doth appall the pride of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Papiſts: our brawling, contentions, and ſtrife, (not for knowledge but for malice) doth bréede a breache for the wicked. But, note that our vnitie &amp; godlineſſe, muſte be a conuerſation, not a déede well done by chaunce at a ſodaine, but a continued conuerſation in holyneſſe: The guide of whiche conuerſation is ſet downe to vs here to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of the Goſpell of God, as from which fountaine euerye manne may fetche hys ſeuerall fruite, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour to life. Marke this you mighty ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and rich of the earth. From hence, namely, from Gods holy worde oughte you firſte (to others godlye example) to draw the patterne to your conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. God ſendeth hys holy Prophets y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the worde, fyrſte to call you hyther. <hi>Goe downe to the houſe of the Kyng of IVDAH,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:29"/> (ſaith the Lord) to Ieremy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 22.1</note> 
                  <hi>and ſpeake thys thing and ſay: heare the worde of the Lord o King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> thou that ſitteſt vpon the throne of Dauid, thou and thy ſeruants and thy people. Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute iudgement and righteouſneſſe, &amp;c. then ſhall yee liue.</hi> I praye you reade the place at youre leyſure you princely Rulers. Know you, that firſt you aboue all menne are ſpectacles and myrrors vnto men: your conuerſation therefore muſte ſhine by the Goſpel; &amp; Gods holy word, and your loue from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue muſt abound in equitie to his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt loue <hi>Aaron</hi> &amp; defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him in truth againſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> malice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. But where is this Goſpel-like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation? We wil aſke of the riche and mighty, nowe at the ende of theſe thrée and twenty yeres but this equall fruit. But it is with vs fruite good ynoughe, for the Miniſter to be baſely eſtéemed, it is no matter to priue his portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to your owne purſes, but ſuche are <hi>Nabothes</hi> &amp; feare not God. I ſpeake not againſt the godly mighty, but againſt the rich men
<pb facs="tcp:8972:29"/> of the earth, whiche care not for theſe wordes: <hi>Do my Prophets no harme:</hi> Nor for this: <hi>He that teacheth the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, let him liue of the Goſpell:</hi> Nor for this: <hi>Muzzel not the mouth of the Oxe, that treadeth out the corne, &amp;c.</hi> But are theſe worldlings but fewe, or rather may we not aſke who is it, that delighteth in this conuerſation of the worde? For the moſte parte ye diſpiſe our holye calling, but daylye more and more, you labour and hunger to be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with our liuings. You are by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling properly temporall, but through el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der abuſe, many of you are become im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly Eccleſiaſticall. The poore Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter muſte crouch to ſuch patrons, his knée to the grounde, his ſtéeple to theyr ſtealth, his tythe to their granary, and his due portion to their vnſatiable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion. Theſe be improper perſons, and therefore (I take it) by law, their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che detentions are rightly called impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Theſe improper per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons receiue hundreds, but the pore Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car can ſcarce haue tenne poundes, and
<pb facs="tcp:8972:30"/> yet the whole burthen is layde on hys ſhoulders. I know not howe many Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the lawe are embrewed wyth this bloude. I am alſo a ſtraunger to the Citie (a poore man come oute of the Country) and whether my Lorde May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or or his brethren be, or haue in their corporation this improper proprietie, I cannot ſay: but I am very ſure of thys, it is a very vnſéemely ſight to ſée a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a Pariſhe Churche, ſo ſtately at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred in ſuche coſtely robes and golden chaines, as the honor of this Citie doth affoorde to hir Aldermen. But if you bée ſuche improper perſons, I pray you yet haue leſſe care of your gaine, and more of conſcience: lette vs not ſerue you for ſuche parings, but ſomewhat more liberally carue to vs in the Lord, we admoniſhe you. Remember, that the word of God requireth you to make vs partakers of all your goodes:<note place="margin">Mala. 1.14.</note> And dare you ſo boldelye take from vs then, our fyrſt allotted portions?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Malach. 3.8</note>It is counted a bleſſed thyng wyth manye, in theſe dayes to ſpoyle the
<pb facs="tcp:8972:30"/> portion of the Miniſter: but the dayes to come ſhall proue it accurſſed with God.</p>
               <p>But (Lorde) this is thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vppon vs thy ſeruauntes why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che haue not ſerued thée, as belongeth vs in theſe thy forbearing dayes, and thy further plague to the poſteritie, for this contempte againſte thée. For thy worde, by thys meanes ſhall bée ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſparingly, or not at all delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them. But ſurelye, if Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates hadde lyttle regarde to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet me ſéemeth it their greate pollicie, whyleſt the LORDE dothe yet forbeare, well to maintaine the preaching miniſtery: For the hart of man is his leader, and the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions kindled there, enforce the bodye ſeruiceable to his will. The handes maye be reſtrained for a time, but the hearte not altered, a newe aſſaye is to be giuen. But if the heart of man bée once conuerted vnto the trueth of God, whyche commeth to paſſe by the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Preaching) then the ſoule
<pb facs="tcp:8972:31"/> ſubmitteth hymſelfe to euerye lawfull power,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1</note> as ſent from God, and for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to GOD, and dutie to hys worde, cauſeth his body to obey, euen to moſte hard commaundements, impoſitions, &amp; euery demannd. Let a ſuruey be taken hereof betwixt the Papiſt, and the true Proteſtant, the one is ready to rebell at euery motion, the other alwayes preſte to aide aucthoritie, with goods, landes, &amp; life. Wherehence commeth this, but that the heartes of men are ſetled by the worde, to ſtoupe and ſtande to their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors ſet ouer them, not for feare, but for conſcience?<note place="margin">Iere. 29.6.7</note> And good <hi>Ieremy</hi> and <hi>Barucke</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baruc. 9.11.12.</note> do euer perſuade the <hi>Iſraell</hi> of God, not only to bende their backes to <hi>Nabuchadnezars</hi> bondage, but alſo har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilye to praye to God for his proſperous raigne, and for the life of his ſonne <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thazar:</hi> how much more then wyl they teache obedience to godlye Princes, by whome God is greately honoured, and his Prophets right louingly intreated? But this is a hard fruite, (o noble Fig-trées, and improrer perſons) to giue to
<pb facs="tcp:8972:31"/> God lame liuings and halting portions, to take the beſte by ſpoile from his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, and your ſelues not ſanctified to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruice. For you are not otherwiſe Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, then when you call for ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, but for the charge of the Cure you take no care. Oh, be afraide of thys, you that forget God, and yet boaſte of hys truth, for it is a right bitter fruite, and roote of a thouſande euils, to the Church of God, whyche is the verye cauſe why I haue thus ſaide vnto it. A braunche whereof, beholde, oure preſente time hathe bredde, for our Miniſters in the Country, for the moſte part, are either ignorant and idle, or elſe ouer poore and néedy. The people, for the moſte, are likewiſe vnder ſuche, either blinde and Popiſhe, or hauty and harde harted, and yet the Lorde doth ſtil beare, and cryeth for better fruites:<note place="margin">Heb. 3.</note> oh (beloued) lette vs hearken to his voice, while it is to day: that we do not ſtil thus fall, by degrées, from the lyuing God, thoroughe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſſe of ſinne. It is ynough that we haue ſpent the time of two and twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:8972:32"/> yeares ſo vainely,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.2.3</note> lette vs knowe that hence forth we ought to liue not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the luſtes of the fleſhe, but after the will of God. But this is a greate won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to manye, that men profeſſing God, and indued with ſo goodlye wits ſhould in the light of the glorious Goſpell (ſo manye yeares gloriouſlye ſhining) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to dwell in ſuche obſtinate blinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But take vppe thy wonder (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) and looke into the matter: So ſhalt thou perceiue this bitter fruit to ariſe of theſe thrée monſtrous vices, namely, <hi>of the carnal contempt of Gods long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feraunce: Of the naturall diſtruſte of his worde and promiſe: And of the preſumptuous abuſe of his goodneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt naturally we feare thoſe things which be angry and able to hurt, as ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, beares, and tyrannous men: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, we doe not feare, but rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempne thoſe thinges whych be milde, &amp; mind not harme, as louyng, kinde, and peaceable men. Yea, ſuche Princes as be rough and ſharp to puniſh tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, wée feare to offende: but ſuche as
<pb facs="tcp:8972:32"/> onely ſtrike of mercies ſtring, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome touch due Iuſtice threat, our wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked nature with tooth &amp; naile, enarmeth hautie contempt againſt them. Euen ſo it is likewiſe to our good God, bicauſe he is ſlow to wrath, &amp; doth not alwayes ſtrike, we ſtraight contemne his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning worde, ſuppoſing, eyther he is not able, or not knowing, to puniſhe our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen rebellion againſte hym, and ſo the wicked ſaieth in his hearte,<note place="margin">Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> there is no God.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondely, if GOD in mercie doe ſwéetely perſuade vs by hys holy worde to true repentaunce, ſtraightwaye our nature halſeth vp a naturall diſtruſte, ſaying:<note place="margin">Malac. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> what profite haue we to ſerue the Lord? or what be his promiſes vnto vs? we wil not hearken vnto his word:<note place="margin">Io. 22.14.15</note> For if we pray vnto him what gaine to vs? In their deadly diſtruſt, they ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſaye:<note place="margin">Ezech 33.</note> Come let vs goe heare what the Lorde wil ſay to vs: but they holde his Prophets as ieſting perſons, and pleaſant Minſtrels that ſatiſfy the time. &amp; not as the ſincere Prophets of God.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8972:33"/>
               <p>For neither beléeue they the promiſes of Gods loue to appertaine to them, or the iudgements of his wrath doe they accepte in truth, and therfore they ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther embrace the promiſſe of his mercy, or be terrified with the threates of hys Iuſtice. But in ſteade therof they ſay: Come, lette vs eate and drincke, for to morrowe we ſhal dye. Oh horrible and thrice curſſed nature, ſo arming thy car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall corps, to abuſe the long ſuffering of thy good God. But be ye ſure, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall worde of God is yea, and Amen, that whatſoeuer it promiſeth, it ſhall performe, and though his infinite wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (to drawe thée to repentaunce) do differ his plagues, yet he wil iuſtifie his worde in the day of his anger. When thoſe thyngs ſhall come to paſſe whych he hath ſpoken by his Prophets, and then in the midle of his wrath, you ſhall confeſſe, that not pleaſaunt Minſtrels, but Gods true Prophetes &amp; Preachers were ſent to forewarne you.<note place="margin">2. Kin. 21.2</note> Theſe bée much more wicked tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> curſſed <hi>Achab,</hi> whyche yet beléeued the worde, at the
<pb facs="tcp:8972:33"/> voice of one Prophet, and receiued co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte: But theſe ſhall haue him a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to their condemnation, in the day of Gods anger, which cannot, or wil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes word, by ſo many yeres trauel amongeſt them.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> But lette vs la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to perſuade you by Gods mercies, to offer vp your bodyes a holy, liuelye, &amp; acceptable ſacrifice to God: whyche is your reſonable ſeruing of God: Tuſh, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not moue, for you beléeue vs not: you haue Papiſticall ſpirites, that is to ſay, doubtfull hearts you dare not reſte vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the promiſes of God, and therefore wil not be allured by his mercies. But let vs tell you,<note place="margin">Eſay. 26 17</note> that if ye followe the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of this worlde, you ſhal die in the ſinnes thereof, you ſaie to your ſelues, ſafe inough, for we haue made a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with death, our Preachers do but ſcare vs, we ſée no ſuche likeneſſe of Gods anger, all thinges continue their courſe as at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning: But you wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully are ignorant, ſaying,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.3.4</note> that the Lord hath a deſire to ſaue vs, and would haue none to periſh, but woulde all to come
<pb facs="tcp:8972:34"/> to repentance. Notwithſtanding, be it knowne to you (O ye curſſed ſcorners) the Lorde wil come to you as a théefe in the night, and when you crye to youre ſelues, peace and reſt, then ſodaine ſhal be your deſtruction,<note place="margin">2. Teſſ. 2.12</note> whiche woulde not credite the worde of trueth to your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.<note place="margin">Gen. 7.</note> The firſt age beleued not <hi>Noah,</hi> and are vniuerſally drowned.<note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> The cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Sodomites</hi> ſcorned <hi>Loth,</hi> and wyth fyre and brimſtone are conſumed. And canſt thou think to eſcape with thy ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning couenant of death, thou Paynim Papiſt, and carnall <hi>Atheiste?</hi> No, the Lord ſaith to euery ſuch, your couenant with death ſhall be diſanulled, and your agréeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with hel ſhal not ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, <hi>When a ſcourge ſhall runne ouer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay. 28.18.</note> 
                  <hi>and paſſe through, then ſhal ye be troden down by it, &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third vice abuſing Gods long ſuffering is, <hi>Our preſumption to ſin:</hi> For we conceiuing by a natural ſelf liking, a ſiniſter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iecture of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, that he doth not ſo narrowly looke to our offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, or will ſo ſtrictly puniſh our ſins: do therfore take occaſion preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly
<pb facs="tcp:8972:34"/> to adde ſin vpon ſin, to paſſe the dayes of our youth, in diſtemperate dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings againſt God &amp; man, promiſing to our ſelues a long life, a long tyme to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, &amp; a long ſuffering God. But (O ye gallants of theſe days) which ſin in this preſumption, know ye, that God is iuſt as he is merciful, &amp; that repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance is his gift, to whom it pleaſeth him, &amp; giuen to the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble ſpirited that feare him: which in the days of their youth reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber him, before thoſe euil dayes come, wherein you ſhal for paine &amp; griefe in conſcience &amp; corps ſay, we haue no pleaſure to liue. Be helping therefore to youre ſelues in God,<note place="margin">Eccle. 12 1.</note> and ſtowpe to the yoke of Chriſte in time. Nowe is the day of your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, when the ſounde of Gods Goſpell ringeth in your eares, now is the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table day: In this day harden not your harts, nor treaſure vp to your ſelues an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger againſt the day of wrath. But lende your luſtie eares to this neceſſarye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde of the Apoſtle <hi>Paule: O man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom 2.4</note> 
                  <hi>deſpiſeſt thou the ryches of hys bountifulneſſe and patience, and long
<pb facs="tcp:8972:35"/> ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, not knowing, that the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulnes of God leadeth thee to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, but thou after thine hardneſſe, and heart that cannot repent, heapeſt vp as a treaſure vnto thy ſelfe, wrath againſt the day of wrath, and of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the iuſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, who wil reward euery man according to his workes.</hi> Now (beloued in God) let vs pray the Lord our long ſuffering God to giue vs true repentaunce, that we abuſe no longer his bleſſed bountie, either with carnall contempte, naturall diffidence, or preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuous ſins: but that with <hi>Dauid</hi> we may praye againſte the rebellion of our youth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> our ſecrete faults and preſumptuous offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, that in this long time of his ſuffering, nowe, dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing ſo neare the Lordes Harueſt, wée may haſten throughe him our heares to be fruitefull, leaſte we ſtill abuſing his great patience, at the laſte ſhall heare to our endleſſe ſorrowe, the ſharpneſſe of this ſentence, <hi>Cutte downe the Figge tree.</hi> But (O Lorde) and deare father graunt vs thy heauenly grace, wée bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéeche
<pb facs="tcp:8972:35"/> thée for thy holy Chriſts ſake.</p>
               <p>And nowe time requireth to ſpeake ſome thing of this ſharpe ſentence, <hi>Cut it downe.</hi> If he had ſaide but, cut it, it had bene a harde word of Gods anger, but in that he ſaith, <hi>Cut it downe,</hi> and with a further demaund, namely, <hi>Why keepeth it the grounde barren alſo?</hi> hée ſignifieth his loue is gone, his wrath is kindled, and therefore this barren trée muſt néedes periſhe.</p>
               <p>Two wicked euils you ſée followeth this wicked Fig trée. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſte, he is not only fruiteleſſe himſelfe, but the verye place where he ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth, he maketh bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly for thys, after a long wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, proyning, wéeding and way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, no goodneſſe founde in him, but much euill, he is commaunded to be cut downe from the trées of the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> And for the firſt, would God it were rightly conſidered of thoſe which are in aucthoritie. For whereſoeuer the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Figge trée abideth, there he is not
<pb facs="tcp:8972:36"/> onely fruiteleſſe to God, but very hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the common weale rounde about him, as for example, the child of hel, the ſhamefull Vſurer, as barren to God, ſo he maketh barren and vnable to liue, al the trées that earſte bare greate ſhewe in that Forreſt of his Countrey. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the hardned Papiſt is not onely an enimy to God, his religion, and hir Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie in his heart, but he maketh accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the valor of his countenaunce, the Countrie by proportion where he dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth very Papiſticall with him. If he be a Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he corrupteth his tenants, and the godly Miniſter there hath ſmall ioy of his labor: but if a Iuſtice of peace (as too manye ſuche there are) then hée goeth very néere (if not) to corrupt ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye his fellowe Benchers, yet by the fleſhly fauor they owe him, and through the linkes of bloude or affinitie to him, or other their friendes, they are become very ſparing of religious fruite, bothe bearing with his Popery, and all hys, and alſo, not ſo dutifull to God, and hir Maieſtie, for the purging of the country
<pb facs="tcp:8972:36"/> of ſuch bitter trées or fruites, as they, of faithfulneſſe oughte, or for their owne perſuaſion ſhould, were they not made barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſuch a bitter Fig trée. Oh Lord why ſhould ſuch vniuſte Papiſts, ſit in place of Iuſtice, ſo to barren the ſoyle rounde aboute them. Mercy they haue had, and it doth rather mar them: Lord, from heauen, from heauen Lord, grant them Iuſtice or mercy at thy good wyll. Conuert them, or confound them Lord: For why ſhoulde they yet make their wiues, their children, their ſeruantes, their tenantes, theyr friendes and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, theyr aſſociates and countrey thy people, hir graces ſubiects in theſe gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing times, ſo mightily barren? Wel, wel, the iolity of theſe, and the number of our owne ſins, haue writhen a coard of maruellous length,<note place="margin">Eſa.</note> to drawe thys heauie ſentence vppon this Nation and people, if we repent not, <hi>Cut it downe.</hi> Thys ſentence is moſt heauy, <hi>Cutte it downe:</hi> But yet it is here intercepted, with a moſt louing petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dreſſer of
<pb facs="tcp:8972:37"/> the Vineyarde, <hi>viz. Lorde, let it alone this yeare alſo, till I digge rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute it and dung it, and if it bring forth fruite, well: if no, then after thou ſhalte cut it downe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Greater glorie God neuer broughte to nation, than to this country of <hi>Iudea,</hi> ſo as the Princely Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid of it: <hi>The Lord hath not dealt ſo with any Nation:</hi> And yet where he beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed his greateſt loue, there they caſte vnto him for thankes the vile ſin of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleſſe ſecuritie, contemning his grace, deſpiſing his lawe, ſlouting hys Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, killing his Chriſte, murthering his Apoſtles, and perſecuting his Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, deteſting his Goſpell, and leading their liues without féeling with the Gentiles in moſte gréedye filthineſſe. Wherefore their glorie is turned into ſhame,<note place="margin">Zach. 11.</note> and the ſtaffe of their beautie, &amp; the band of his couenante is broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al to péeces, and they commaunded to vtter ruine, <hi>Cut it downe.</hi> Oh that <hi>Englande</hi> would looke to this. More beautie, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bandes of Gods amitie hath not bin
<pb facs="tcp:8972:37"/> ſéene, no not in <hi>Iewrie,</hi> yet <hi>Englande</hi> is too careleſſe what ſhe giueth God: She taketh an argument fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his former fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and louing band of peace, to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate into a perpetual reſte, but ſhe remembreth not that <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> are cut down, nor throughly weyeth the cauſe crauing like cenſure nowe. In truth (beloued trée of <hi>Englande</hi>) were it not for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> interception of thy dreſſers pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, the interceſſion of thy only medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour Ieſus Chriſt, ther is no let of this ſentence againſte thée, <hi>Cut it downe.</hi> Conſider then with thankefulneſſe (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) who is thy ſafetie, <hi>Euen Ieſus Chriſte alone our mightie Michaell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Daniel 12.1</note> that ſtandeth in the gap theſe <hi>22.</hi> yeares for thée. But here we may not forget, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt our dreſſer &amp; defender to God his father doth <hi>2.</hi> things for his church.<note place="margin">Ezech. 22 3</note> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The one is, as a vigilant paſtor &amp; defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, he is redy to help, preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at néed, &amp; taketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oportunitie offred, to benefite the ſame: For euen at that inſtant, when God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth to deſtroy the trée, at that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, he maketh his harty petition for it.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8972:38"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The other is Chriſtes prayer for his people, but vnder a condition, <hi>Spare it Lorde (ſaith he) &amp;c. till I digge it, if then it bring fruite, wel: but if no, thou ſhalt cutte it downe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of Chriſts vigilancie ouer this land, for hir defence, we haue moſte ſingular aſſurance, and the ſame ſhall appeare moſte plainely vnto vs, if we looke into the ancient ſins of the ſame, in hir elder people, and his ſentence, executed vppon them after hys long ſufferyng, for that there wanted a Mediator at laſt to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the gap. And in ſinceritie of our harts doe then leuell the line of oure wicked conuerſation, with the ſins of our ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, &amp; his defending arme vpon vs, we ſhal be driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to acknowledge his louing vigilancie to be our only ſtay. The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient <hi>Brytanes</hi> the firſte Fathers of thys Iland, did liue after Chriſts incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in abundant wealth, but they gaue themſelues (ſaith the ſtorie) to the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie of the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> to the diſdaine of the truth, and to great looſeneſſe of life, ſo as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Nobilitie &amp; Clergie were wholy
<pb facs="tcp:8972:38"/> giuen to <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Venus.</hi> The Lord firſt ſent them warnings, then warres with the <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> whych mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moleſted them. But what didde theſe brute <hi>Brytanes?</hi> They returned not to the Lorde, confeſſing their ſins, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting theyr wicked liues, repoſing their confidence in Gods hande, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in their luſte ſtil, they ſente for aide againſt the enimy to the <hi>Saxons,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yere of Chriſt <hi>685.</hi> which was the firſt meſſage of their ouerthrowe. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord in his iuſte iudgement vſed them his inſtruments to driue the <hi>Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes</hi> into <hi>Wales,</hi> where they remaine as yet, &amp; theſe their confederates poſſeſſed thys pleaſant Iland. So came the <hi>Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes</hi> vnder this Cenſure, <hi>Cutte them down.</hi> Likewiſe the <hi>Saxons</hi> poſſeſſing this lande, and abuſing Gods bleſſings, gaue themſelues to a declining from God and his truth, and charity was key cold amongſt them. Whiche two horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vices can neuer dwel alone, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ignorance came into the countrey, and tooke poſſeſſion of the Churche.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8972:39"/>
               <p>It was a wonder (ſaith the Booke) to haue a Prieſt to vnderſtand his Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. The Nobilitie became <hi>Atheistes</hi> and wicked men, the common people were ſolde to ſinne: For pride, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and drunkenneſſe entred into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from high Palaces. Niceneſſe of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, had then a common habite wyth men: for newe deuiſes were euery day. And (that which is not at this day amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the reſte to be forgotten) the <hi>Saxons</hi> did in very muche brauery clip or ſhaue their beards to the very face, all excepte onely the ouer lippe. But the Lorde (as greatelye grieued at the Lande, by ſome good Biſhops reproued them, and when no admonition coulde preuaile, he bente the heauens wyth blazing Comets, to threaten this Sentence: <hi>Cutte the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xons down.</hi> For, <hi>Anno. <hi>1066.</hi>
                  </hi> after the Comet, came <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Norman,</hi> and did execute that ſentence vpon the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> conquering the lande, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threwe the former ſtate. O deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in God, can wée <hi>Engliſhemen</hi> ſée our noble trée thus twice cutte downe,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:39"/> and not quake for feare of like iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? or is there not like cauſe in vs, ſo to procure Gods wrath? Be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, GOD is not mocked, neither come I to flatter, or yet to feare to ſpeak the truth. <hi>Englande</hi> is full of ſickneſſe, byles and ſoares, procuring death. We may truely lament, for it is as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Micah</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Micah. 7.12.3.</note> did for his people, ſaying: <hi>Wo is me, for I am as the Sommer ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therings, and as the Grapes of the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, there is no cluſter to eate, my ſoule deſired the firſte ripe fruites. The goodman is periſhed out of the earth, and there is no righteous among men. They all laye waite for bloude, euery man hunteth his brother with a nette.</hi> By this ſentence the Prophet accuſeth his people of <hi>3.</hi> peſtiferous euils: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the firſte is <hi>a Catholike backeſliding from religion &amp; godlineſſe</hi> ſaying: <hi>the good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is periſhed</hi> for thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> remain, are but rare &amp; thin, euen the gleanings of the Harueſt, and as the Vine trée, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Vintage whiche maye happilye haue here and there one Grape lefte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind.
<pb facs="tcp:8972:40"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>of a general hipocriſie,</hi> for he ſaith: <hi>Nemo rectus,</hi> No man trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth by the meaſure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> line, whych his profeſſion &amp; calling doth leuil vnto him, but maketh a ſhew of another than that he is indéede. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And laſte, <hi>of an vniuerſal crueltie,</hi> vſing the Metaphor, <hi>Euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth his brother with a net.</hi> And my brethren lette vs examine the common condition of moſt parts now in <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de,</hi> ſhal not we perceiue theſe ſins to abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the ſame: looke to our earneſt profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Goſpell, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of hir Maieſties raigne (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie long preſerue ouer vs, &amp; euer in hys Chriſt) how we hungred the truth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how we ioyed of Gods Miniſters, how we deſired heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly encreaſe, &amp; prepared our liues to anſwere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel: we clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our Churchs, our hearts &amp; houſes of popiſh Idolatry, we reedified y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſquire of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in ſuch zeale (name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Potentates, Biſhops, Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> &amp; other many godly ones) as we were no whit inferior to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Iewes,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che with <hi>Nehemias</hi> &amp; <hi>Ezra</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſra. 3. &amp; 5 Nehe. ca. 3. ca. 4.</note> repayred the
<pb facs="tcp:8972:40"/> ruinous walles of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> But (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) let vs with a ſimple eye, looke into euery ſtate almoſt in <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> now, &amp; we ſhal right ſorowfully ſée a catholike coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of this former zeale to Gods houſe. Partly by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> malice of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants the Papiſts, ſéeking by perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; al policie, to hinder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former work, offring vs their help to build, whoſe pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe is, wholy to pul down: And partly,<note place="margin">Eſra. 4.2.</note> by our owne wearineſſe of well doing, which contenting oure ſelues with our firſte building,<note place="margin">Haggai. 12.4.</note> haue taken ſurceſſe for a time, to build &amp; pul downe, &amp; rebuild a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine (to our great coſt, &amp; the Countries great paine) our braue bowers &amp; ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous towers, to féed our fantaſies, and pore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s eies: but the building of Gods holy houſe, to the encreaſe of faith &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we haue almoſt laide aſide, except a few ſommer gatherings, by grace conſerued vnto God. May wée not therfore admoniſh Magiſtrats, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters &amp; godly men, to apply this voice of the ſpirite of God to his holy churche, which firſte was ſente to <hi>Epheſus? viz.
<pb facs="tcp:8972:41"/> I knowe thy workes (ſayth God) and thy labour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and thy patience, and how thou canſte not forbeare them whych are euil, and haſt examined the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſay they are Apoſtles and are not, and haſte found them lyars, and haſte ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered (for my names ſake) and haſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and for my names ſake haſte la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured, and haſte not fainted. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, I haue ſomewhat againſt thee, bycauſe thou haſte lefte thy firſt loue. Remember therefore from whence thou haſte fallen, and repent and doe thy firſte workes, or elſe I will come ſhortly and remoue thy Candleſticke.</hi> We are all leſſe louing, leſſe labouring, and leſſe zealous in religion, than earſt we haue béene: yea, one and all of vs, which the Lordes ſpirite (the true diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerner of all things) doth call here a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from our firſt loue, and threatneth a comming to cut vs downe, if we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent not his ſpéedy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to our can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks. O Lord for thy mercies ſake, graunt to our godly Prince, and all hir noble Counſellors: to the Biſhops and
<pb facs="tcp:8972:41"/> learned Fathers, to the Iudges, Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and godly people (thoughe Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer gatherings) thy grace, that they may all in their callings and ſpirites, take hold of their firſt loue, and do their firſte good workes, in thée, and by thy Chriſte, that our Candleſticke (thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goſpel and Church, hir Maieſtie, and this our hapy ſtate) may firmely ſtand to thy glory, and our continuall comfort for thy holy names ſake. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But if ther be ſuch a weakneſſe in Gods Sommer ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therings in <hi>England,</hi> whiche yet are the beſt beloued of the Lord: what are wée to looke for in the reſt, whyche are but hypocriticall? <hi>Nemo rectus,</hi> (ſayth the Prophet) No man kéepeth hys heart, and his hand, by that line that the lawe of his God, &amp; the ſimplicitie of his ſoule, doth direct vnto him. And ſurely, if you wil not wilfully be blinde, when didde you euer reade, heare, or ſée of greater hypocriſie, than is nowe reſiante in <hi>Englande?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Papiſt ſuppoſeth, it his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt grace to coulour his Italian hearte
<pb facs="tcp:8972:42"/> with hys Papiſticall hypocriſie: For lette hym bée accompted Papiſticall by the ſuperiours, and Lorde, howe hée proteſteth the contrarye, and if hys inferioure enforme him, then he frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, ſweateth, ſweareth, and taketh it hotely: but yet there is no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter poyſon in the Toade, nor fixed hatred in the Serpente, or rigoure in the roaryng Lyon huntyng for hys praye,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> than lurketh vnder the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred tongues of oure Italienated Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes: For the poiſon of Aſpes is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their lippes. Againe, what diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation amongeſt menne of all ſorts in eache degrée? O Lorde, it is a worlde to ſée <hi>Abels</hi> countenaunce, but <hi>Caines</hi> hearte amongeſt confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, friendes, parteners and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brethren vniuerſallye abroade. It hathe béene called the holy water of the Courte, but in euerye corner of the lande at thys daye are greate Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprings of this infernall Lake. If yée buy but corne of the huſbandmanne, there is deceit, if you deale with the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificer,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:42"/> beholde ſwéete wordes, and ſleightie ſubtiltie. But trafique, or craue counterchaunge with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunte or Vſurer in Citie or Towne, (excepte ſome ſpeciall man of GOD) and beholde a graue countenaunce, a ſugred tong, and ſéemely welcome: but if thou deale wyth hym, he is as a thornie hedge. Thou takeſt hym for a ſhilter, but if he haue delyuered thy clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes from ſome ſtormy raine: yet ere thou eſcape from vnder him, he will all to ſcratch thy fleſhe: If he bit thee not to the very bones. Oh ſéeming friendſhip, and ſure hypocriſie. O Lorde preſerue thy holy miniſtery from hypocriſie, and kéepe hir farre from Iuſtice ſeate. But <hi>Micah</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Micah. 7.3.</note> ſaide in his time of it thus: <hi>To make good for the euil of his handes, the Prince (viz. the great Rulers in the lande) asked, and the iudge iudged, for a rewarde, therfore the great man, hee ſpeaketh oute the corruption of hys hearte, and ſo they wrappe it vppe. The beſte of them is as a bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar, and the moſte righteous of them
<pb facs="tcp:8972:43"/> is ſharper than a thorny hedge. The daye of thy watchemen, and thy viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation commeth, then ſhall bee theyr confuſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No maruayle (beloued) for a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall iniquitie, can not but begette an vniuerſall cutting downe. Woulde God hypocriſie had not ſpred his wings ſo largely in <hi>Englande,</hi> &amp; pierced ſo déepe as to the harts of many ſorts in hir, or ſo cunningly couloured his vgly ſhape, as he hathe at this day. For no where ſhal religion, godlineſſe, or honeſty offer hir ſelfe in <hi>England:</hi> but hypocriſie dare ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture to preſume of ſome preferment in that place. He is the veſture of the proude, the habite of the adulterer, the gowne of the Vſurer, and the beſte at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre for the <hi>Macheuil.</hi> The <hi>Atheist</hi> gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth him about him, and no treaſon can be broched beſides him. He delighteth not to dwell with beggers, but offereth ſalutations to ſacred ſtates, the Lorde graunte all godly Princes and Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates eies to ſée hym, and ſpirites to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne him, for his glorye and oure beſte
<pb facs="tcp:8972:43"/> good.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> But haue we likewiſe vniuerſall Crueltie? and doe wée lay watch to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall our brethren? ſurely, thys ſinne is too vniuerſall. What Village, Towne, or Citie is it, that is not a witneſſe vnto this?<note place="margin">Gen. 10.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Nymrod</hi> was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a greate Hunter, but <hi>Nymrods</hi> hunting is nothing worth: he hunted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beaſtes and buildings, but wée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte our brethren. And ſurely thys hunting muſte néedes be vniuerſall, while it hathe taken holde of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie. Doe not hir maieſties Courtes approue greate hunting with a Nette leaſe often, twelue, or twenty yeares to come, is hunted ſo after, with a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous <hi>Nymrod</hi> nowe, that his poore bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whyche dothe enioye it, muſte of neceſſitie, eyther take a newe, or bée in feare to bée foreſtalled of hys ſtate to come. No offices ſo baſe, that ſundry nettes of dyuers webbes, are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided to foreſtall them. No forfeite, bée it ſmall, but gréedily ſome one doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute agaynſte an other by meanes
<pb facs="tcp:8972:44"/> whereof, ſinne is dailye ſolde for ſiluer For the informer taketh his bribe, and lets the faulte remaine. No intreaty, perſuaſion, or louing deſire, can winne the poore, but little fauour in this cruell age. Such dyking in of groundes, ſuche barring menne of common righte, as the poore Cottier muſte eyther begge, and bée ſtarued, or elſe ſteale and bée hanged: For ſo menne hunte after bloude. The Countrey Villages doe decaye, and ſhire Townes are fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led wyth beggers: for rotten ſhéepe do ouer runne all. Oh Lorde, ceaſe thys crueltie.<note place="margin">Habac. 2.12.</note> The Prophet <hi>Haba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cucke</hi> cryed out of them in olde tyme, whyche buylded Townes wyth bloud <hi>viz.</hi> rapine, oppreſſion, and cruelty.</p>
               <p>But he hathe lefte it alſo to thée in writing, which pulleſt down Townes, to féede thy owne couetouſneſſe wyth pore mennes bloude: <hi>Ho</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>hee that coueteth an euill couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to hys houſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Habac. 2.9</note> 
                  <hi>that hee maye ſet hys neſte on hyghe, to eſcape from
<pb facs="tcp:8972:44"/> the power of euill, thou haſte conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſhame, to thine owne houſe, by deſtroying manye people, and haſte ſinned agaynſte thine owne ſoule: for the ſtone ſhal crye out of the wall, and the beame out of the timber ſhall aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare it,</hi> And concerning the Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, ſuch ſpiteful crueltie is bent againſt it, as it paſſeth, not onelye by others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte vs, but euen of one of vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte an other.</p>
               <p>It is a greate crueltie, my Lordes, and Fathers of the lawe, that ſundrye godlye Preachers in this land, lyuing obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> now eſtabliſhed laws, haue bene poſſeſſed of their benefices for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye yeares, ſhall be no more regarded than a dumbe Dogge, a blinde Idoll Prieſt, that can nothyng ſaye: Nay, by ſome ſuche wicked perſons and their complices, Noble menne, and greate menne of aucthoritie ſhall be abuſed, yea, reachyng ſometime to the hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Gouernoures, to flitte good mennne oute of theyr ſeates. I coulde name ſome ſuche lewde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:45"/> and wil, if I be demaunded, that make an occupation to eſpy aduantage, making no difference of men, for their filthie gaine, to thruſt out godly Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chars from the Church of God, and for theyr fée, to thruſte the greateſt giuer into ſuch roomths. Theſe are ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Hunters whyche hunt ſome twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſome thyrty, ſome forty yeares paſt, for forfaites of Benefices, to ſette Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony on ſale. I beſéeche your Lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips aydes and helpes for Gods church herein, that if you wante lawe for theſe men, your endeuour may be to procure further, as time and grace will offer it. Wante lawe ſayde I? nay my Lordes, you had néede go afreſh to your Books, and ſtudye more law, againſte the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie of theſe dayes: For, what ſay you (learned Fathers) to this cunning cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie. A patrone of a Benefice, giueth his Benefice fréely, fearing the ſtrict ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of ſome good Biſhoppe, ſo as the poore Clearke to be inſtituted by his preſentation, may ſafely ſwere and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, that he hath giuen nothing, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb facs="tcp:8972:45"/> nothing, either money or leaſe, he or hys friendes: but the patrone cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the friendes of the partie preſented, and bindeth them in a greate ſumme, that whenſoeur the ſame ſhall be inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and inducted, he ſhal at any time, within one moneth, after ſuche his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, at the demaunde of the ſaid pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone, or his aſſignes, abſolutely reſigne v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe hys ſayde Bene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yre. But what is the purpoſe of this crueltie? Forſoothe, eyther to compel the incumbent hauing paſſed the Byſhops handes, to leaſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the couetous patrone, that bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice at his owne price, or elſe to thruſte him quite out of that ſeate, for an other Chapman. O horrible and moſt grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous crueltie: I ſpeake not by geſſe, but by certaine knowledge hereof, yet not in mine owne caſe, I praiſe God for it. But if cruelty be crepte ſo high, as it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ſo againſte the Miniſters of God: ſhall we not thinke ſhe hath greate au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in the temporall ſorte? I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not here to ſaye more of the ſinnes of <hi>Englande:</hi> but be you Iudges (O ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable
<pb facs="tcp:8972:46"/> audience, whether the petition of our Mediator hathe not hitherto moſt mightily preuailed againſte our deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſentence, <hi>Cut it downe.</hi> But now lette vs conſider likewiſe of Chriſtes conditionated prayer for the Figge trée. <hi>Till I digge it, and dung rounde about it: if it bring forth fruite, then well: If no, then after thou ſhalte cut it down.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is prayer with condition, the condition hath in it thys: Firſte, the labour of the dreſſer, and alſo of the good ſucceſſe of the trée. I will digge it and dung it, ſaith the dreſſer of the bitter Figge trée. That is, I will do to it that thing, which, if there be any life in it, ſhall without doubte make it fruitfull. The great mercie of God doth ſtill yet abounde (beloued) and the ſingular loue of this oure Mediatoure Chriſte, héere alſo, that when the daye of deſtruction is preparing, euen then the Father by the mediation of the ſonne is ſtayed from ſtriking, to a further ſeaſon. But Chriſte will digge, and Chriſte will dung his Churche this Realme, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb facs="tcp:8972:46"/> Fig trée to take awaye by the one, the corruptions and impediments that may hinder his fruitetulneſſe: And by the other to ſhelter him, ſupple, and moyſten his roote, that the vigor, whych there is cowched as ſcante kéeping life, ſhould valiantly aſpyre the top of ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt twigges, and mightily make them fruitefull. And this holye operation Chriſte our Lorde, worketh from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by his ſubſtitutes and Miniſters in earth, namely, his Magiſtrates, Ciuil &amp; Eccleſiaſticall: his holy ſpirite by them diggeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trées at the roote, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorie of his name, in conuerting and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firming the Figge trée, or in Iuſtice and equity to <hi>cut downe the ſame.</hi> And here you Gouernors vnder God, you muſt learn from Chriſt two eſpeciall leſſons: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that you haue ſuche a Fatherly loue to your charge and people co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to you as Chriſt our Maiſter had, and to be frée fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe euils your ſelues, whiche cauſe this heauy ſentence to the Fig trée, <hi>cut it down.</hi> Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, to be vigilant, ſober &amp; wiſe, to diſcern y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:8972:47"/> petition to the Lorde, and to digge and dung the trée, and to ſtande in the gappe againſte the Lordes wrath. To the firſte, <hi>Moſes</hi> giueth example, to al Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and (beſides oure Chriſte in thys Parable) <hi>Amos</hi> the Prophet to al Gods Miniſters. And feare you not good ſucceſſe of youre prayer and youre godly trauel: for thys Parable and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places of Gods Booke, doe hearten you hereto: namely, the Lorde by the Prophet <hi>Ezechiell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezec. 22.26</note> who, accuſing the Prieſtes to haue broken hys lawe, to haue defiled the Sacrifices, and propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Sabbothes: The Princes to be rauenous as wolues, and to deſtroye ſoules for theyr couetous lucar: The Prophets and Preachers to haue daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed them (that is, flattered their vices) with vntempered morter, to ſaye, thus ſayth the Lord, when the Lorde ſpake not ſo: The people of the lande by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and robery, vexed the pore and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and oppreſſed the ſtranger agaynſt righte: all whyche prouoked Gods greate anger, and their deadly deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:47"/> yet to the comforte of the ciuill and Eccleſiaſticall Gouernors: he there ſayth:<note place="margin">Verſe. 30.31</note> 
                  <hi>And I ſoughte for a manne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that ſhoulde make vppe the hedge, and ſtand in the Gappe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mee for the lande, that I ſhoulde not deſtroye it, but I founde none: Therefore haue I powred out mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation vppon them, and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them with the fyre of my wrath. Theyr owne wayes haue I rendered vppon theyr heades, ſayth the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Note wel thys, howe God in hys an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſéeketh for hys Gods and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in earth, to haue theyr laboure, to dygge and dung, to hedge and ſtande in the breach againſt God, if his venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance be commyng: and they ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile. If the loue of <hi>Moſes</hi> be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, as wée haue greate cauſe to confeſſe it, and the bowelles of pitie in our fathers and Miniſters of the church of <hi>England:</hi> No doubte they will pray for vs, they wyll endeuour to make vs fruitefull. Of whoſe loue, for breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſake I ſend the Magiſtrates to <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odus,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:48"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8972:48"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8972:49"/> 32.31.</hi> and the fatherly Paſtor to <hi>Amos</hi> the Prophet. <hi>7.1.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Then, to diſcerne the time of ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the gappe, is right neceſſary for the godlye Magiſtrates in earth, and when to be moſte earneſt to digge and dung the Figge trée: And that is, euen when elſe the Lorde woulde deſtroy it, and ſaith, <hi>Cutte it downe.</hi> God vſeth not nowe to ſpeake to vs, but by his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Preachers, whiche be ordinary and extraordinary. His ordinary Preachers (our dayly Paſtors) we knowe, and by his great mercy féele the great bleſſings of God in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. His extraordinary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets are partely from heauen, partelye from earth. The Lorde by theſe dothe teache vs into his obedience, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warneth vs of his plagues, when they perceiue oure iniquitie to growe into ripeneſſe.<note place="margin">Amos.</note> And ſurely the Lord doth ſtil open his ſecreates to his Prophets, and doth giue them eyes, to diſcerne hys iudgements, comming by his former hande vppon like tranſgreſſions. They are called our watchemen, and ſurely,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:49"/> we muſte yéelde them credite,<note place="margin">Ezech. 33.</note> when rightly they ring the Alarma, or elſe we periſh. And that they myghte not be deceiued, God hathe in hys worde tolde them when to praye, and to ſtirre vppe the Magiſtrates to digge and giue compoſe. But when bothe the tokens in the worde, and the extraordinarie Preachers of Gods ſworde doe crye to vs, beware this ſentence, <hi>Cutte it downe:</hi> then it behoueth to digge and dung, that is, to take awaye that and thoſe things whiche hinder the fruite of the Figge trée, and to adde and laye to it, that which maye comforte, ſupple, and moyſten the roote therof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The time when to praye, to digge and dung the Figgetrée is, when the Bridegrome is departed from his ſpouſe for a ſeaſon in diſpleſure, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt his church mourne, and his Prophets pray, as it is <hi>Math, 9.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, when God by his extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Prophets in earth, and from Heauen dothe crye to vs the foreſaide heauy ſentence, then it is highe time to digge and dung the Figge trée, <hi>Eſay. 22.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8972:50"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> But the Bridegrome is abſent from thys Church, when in hir peace by hir owne wantonneſſe and wilfull diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſhe turneth to hir ſtubborne hart, to loath his worde and fruitefull voice, recallyng hir Fathers houſe, to hir affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 4.5.</note> and by the luſte of carnall <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt,</hi> doth quench in hir y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purity of loue, and dothe giue hir ſelfe to hir owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyghtes, ſo as hir huſbande Chriſte can take no pleaſure in hir company. Thys is wel ſignified to vs by the Pſalmiſte, in the <hi>45.</hi> Pſalme verſe <hi>10.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.10.</note> by the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite doctrine: <hi>Hearken o daughter</hi> (ſaith Chriſte to his eſpouſed Churche) <hi>and conſyder and incline thine eare: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gette alſo thy fathers houſe, (that Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giptiacall and idolatrous houſe) So ſhall the Kyng take pleaſure in thy beautie: For he is thy Lorde, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence thou hym.</hi> But by that wée haue ſufficiently ſayde, and the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence offered to eache man euery day, we maye clearely ſée, that our Preachers haue, at this very inſtant, great cauſe to call to mourning. For the loue to oure
<pb facs="tcp:8972:50"/> Bridegrome Chriſte is almoſt al ſpent, we waxe weary of his worde, we take vs to our owne direction, and beginne to diſlike to be ruled longer by it: For the Papiſtes will not heare, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doth not conſider his backeſliding from his former loue, neither inclineth with an obedient eare to the voice of the Bridegroome: but our delights are who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſette, if not in the golden Calfe, yet to eate and drinke, and riſe vppe to playe, as erſt we did, euen as the Gentiles,<note place="margin">Exod. 32 6. 1. Cor. 10.7.</note> which knewe not God, and that wyth gréedineſſe: but brethren we haue not ſo learned Chriſte.<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.19.</note> Gods Prophets ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, and this to growe ſo greate, as growing all abroade, and for the ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it, ready to the Harueſt, wyth one conſent they crye to <hi>Englande,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 3.2</note> 
                  <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent for the kingdome of God is at hande.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe. 10.</note> Nowe is the Are laide to the trée, therefore euery trée which bringeth not forth good fruite, is hewen downe and caſt into the fire. But they crye and lament with <hi>Eſay, Lorde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 53.1. Rom. 10.16</note> 
                  <hi>who is it that beleeueth our ſaying?</hi> Wherefore
<pb facs="tcp:8972:51"/> it behoueth you my Lords, &amp; Gods Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, to ioyne the ſworde with the worde, and more forcibly yet to digge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute the Figge trée. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of Gods extraordinary Preachers from Heauen, and with vs here in this land, and marke wel, whether there be not a conſent, of bothe in this matter, to ſommone vs to iudgement. From Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen God by fire, hathe ſommoned thys land to repentance (<hi>Anno. <hi>1581.</hi> primo Elizab.</hi> when in that tempeſt this moſt notable monument (of <hi>Paules</hi> Churche) by whyche we ſtand, and is now in our eyes, he, to ſhewe his kindled wrath, ſet fire vppon the ſpier of it, whych was the beautie of the lande. And Chriſtianlye conſider it (brethren) it beganne not at the Church, leaſt men might haue ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined it, to haue come of trechery or neg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligence, but from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bowle down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, that one and all might ſée it, to be the only worke of God. Manye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches this noble citie hath like ſubiecte vnto GOD, but hys good pleaſure was to make choice of thys
<pb facs="tcp:8972:51"/> (the moſte notable Beacon of the land) as thereby to expreſſe his anger vnto al, if we repent not. Againe, the fire fel not on our dwelling houſes at home, but only on the houſe of God: Euen therby, not only to conuince vs of ſinne, for the abuſe of hys holy Temple, but alſo to ſignifie to the beſte of oure ſoules, that wée whyche beare the name of GOD, &amp; his religion in our profeſſion, haue not in ſinceritie aunſwered oure faith, and therefore are vnder the cenſure of Gods anger. And ſurely, thys double abuſe is greate this daye in <hi>Englande:</hi> For there is no place ſo egregiouſly polluted as the Churche of <hi>Paules,</hi> or his worde more contemned in any place. What meaneth elſe that accuſtomed walking, and prophane talking in time of the Sermon there? Neither is there any Nation more bleſſed wyth puritie of godly doctrine in trueth, or any (ſo bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) leſſe fruitefull vnto GOD. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I confeſſe it, with thankfulneſſe to God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his Goſpel hath won to hym, infinite ſoules in this nation which doe
<pb facs="tcp:8972:52"/> the Lorde, his holy word, Sacraments, and Sabaoth, as well in thys Citie, as in the realme abroade. But at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of thys firie Preacher, we then cryed (namelye thys Citie, hir Graces Courte, and the whole lande) Lord, we haue ſinned, ſpare thy people O Lorde: And ſo our mediatour Chriſt ſtayed the fire. And then alſo the Lorde ſtirred vp the heartes of our honorable aucthoritie to giue from hir Maieſtie, Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to take away the abuſe thereof, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was an approued digging: but alas, how long did we obey? euen but a ſhort ſpace, for as the lawe came but for that houſe of ſtone, ſo our ſtony heartes, caſt off with ſpéede, the verye memorie of this iuſte threatning Preacher. And nowe who maketh accompts of it? wel, wel: nay, woe, woe, to vs, if we ſo looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looke about vs. O Lord, what harts haue wée? Shall a ſodaine falling of a rotten and olde Turret of <hi>Syloah,</hi> be by our Maiſter Chriſte inſtituted a doctour of repentance to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> (for the fall whereof reaſon coulde afforde vs ſome
<pb facs="tcp:8972:52"/> cauſe) and ſhall wée, or dare we ſo deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe this ſpeciall meſſenger from God, this burned ſtéeple, whych calleth vs al to daily repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance? Come hither to me, ye commers to the Citie (ſaith Paules ſtéeple) and beholde the anger of oure God. For as ye ſée me, ſo I remayne corrected by his reuenging hande, to cal you to repentance. But O Lorde, thou God of Heauen, this Citie, this land, this place, yea this day hath forgotten this. Make vs mindefull (O Lorde) of thée, and penitently ſorrowfull for oure ſinnes againſt thée, we humbly beſéeche thée for Chriſtes ſake. And as Gods ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary preachers came not alone, but had ſome one or other ioyned vnto them, as <hi>Eſay</hi> had <hi>Micah, Ieremy</hi> had <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> and <hi>Hoſeas</hi> had <hi>Amos:</hi> So this fire from Heauen hathe to aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate his meſſage in earth Gods ſwift ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, and burning ſword of peſtilence, chieflye in this Citie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.5.6.</note> from whence it hathe bin ſundry times, in ſundrye pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces diſperſed, and in ſuche ſorte, as oure gracious Quéene, &amp; godly Magiſtrates
<pb facs="tcp:8972:53"/> haue gyuen forth holy lawes for prayer and faſting, to moue the people to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, thereby acknowledging this ſword to be far other, and beyond natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cauſe of infection. From heauen we haue hadde alſo a thirde extraordinary Preacher of Gods anger, and warning to repentaunce, whych hath bin termed, <hi>The gentle warning,</hi> the Lorde make vs méeke ſpirited in humble ſorte, to bée rightly warned by it. But howſoeuer it fare with vs, yet theſe termes and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly actes doe approue theſe for Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ſent of GOD, and that (by our conſent in worde and déede) to our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warning. The blazing Starres I ſpeake not of, as hauing foreſighte to ſée thys cauill: and why they to <hi>Englande</hi> more than to other countries? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I care to giue vs our own meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. From earth alſo the Lorde hathe moſte notably cited vs to iudgement, &amp; ſignified his ſentence ready to be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but for the mediation of our Chriſt, and that alone. What meaneth elſe that monſtrous mouing of that twentye
<pb facs="tcp:8972:53"/> acres of grounde, <hi>Anno. <hi>1570.</hi>
                  </hi> as oure allowed Chronicles do reporte? or ſuch ſundry inundation of waters in euerye coaſt of our Country? Such monſtrous byrthes, ſtrange ſickneſſes, and ſodaine deaths? But laſte of all,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>An.</hi> 1580. <hi>Aprilis.</hi> 6</note> that vniuerſall Earthquake, and like waterſhake, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che draue vs into preſent feare, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the whole ſtate to Chriſtian prayer, and care to repent? If nowe the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of our time haue not cauſe to ſay, Our God is angrie and prepared vnto battel? wherfore alſo I would not haue you to forgett our preſent Iriſhe wars, which, although they be farre from the hearte, yet God graunte vs to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that his power is greate, our ſins are ripe, and the enimies purpoſe, (that traiterous Doctor <hi>Saunders</hi> and his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents) right daungerous, But if wée truely turne to the Lorde, he will turne to vs and them, with theyr aides, to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confuſion, as his grace hath ſhewed himſelf a louing God to vs, in their late ouerthrowe in thoſe parts, his name for euer be praiſed.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8972:54"/>
               <p>Nowe beloued Magiſtrates of bothe eſtates your office is at this inſtant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, to digge and giue compoſe, and aboue all, you muſt take care that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the gappe to ſtoppe the breache for the people, you be not like wicked, as the people: for their ſhall you periſhe before them, and great ſhall be our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. The Lorde Mayor muſte not be a Proteſtaunt, during his office, and a Papiſt after, and ſo for his office ſake, ſhewe himſelfe occupied about the Fig trée of his City: but he with his brethren ought to be touched and ſealed in hearte to the Lorde, that at all times, as they are preferred to their people, ſo they bée godly, religious, vpright, &amp; holye aboue the people, that their prayer and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian practize maye ben defence for the Citie, not onely againſt the pernitious purpoſe of the euill diſpoſed: but alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the iuſt reuenging hand of God, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he warneth vs of iminent danger. So likewiſe muſte the Biſhoppes thoſe reuerende Fathers, and the other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours and gouernors abroade be, and
<pb facs="tcp:8972:54"/> haue the ſame condition engrauen in their ſpirite with the penſil of God, that they may repaire the broken hedge, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue the hindering matter from the roote of the Fig trée, and lay compoſe to moiſten, ſupple, and comforte the life therof. Which grace God grant you for your ſelues, and vs for Chriſtes ſake. But our texte doth directe your holy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours vnto two things: Firſt, that you take from the trée, that whiche doth hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the growth to the fruit therof: Then that you lay to the roote of the ſame that dung or compoſe whiche may admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter helpe to the life of it. But I praye you lette pore <hi>Haggai</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Haggai. 1.1.</note> delyuer vnto <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robabel</hi> and <hi>Iehoſuah</hi> the thing whiche mightily doth hinder the growth of the Figge trée, whych may ſéeme to youre diſcretions, ſo muche more worthye of receit, as that the ſame is ſente to youre memories, by that Princely Prophet <hi>Dauid.</hi> And it is that:<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Zorobabell</hi> and <hi>Iehoſuah,</hi> (of a milde purpoſe) haue v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the enimies of thys trée ſuch mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſſe pitie, that by ſuche ouermuche le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:55"/> thrée peſtilent cancre wormes are bred in the earth about the roote, and eate vppe the life of the Figge trée. But if they be not with ſpéed digged and caſt away, to the helpe of his life, it is of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, that he muſte be cut down. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſte is the cancre of Popiſhe conſpyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and their wicked counſell. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde is, the ſtiffe and ſtubborne ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in ſinne and the defence thereof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And the thirde is, that the ſcorning A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, peſtilent Papiſte, and ſubtile hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite are ſet with, and aboue the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chayre of aucthority, which is (by their abuſe) become greately the chaire of ſcorners. If thys earth be not remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, the Cancre wormes excéedinglye bréede, and the barren trée muſt periſhe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The conſpiracies of the Papiſtes, and their wicked cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels they be eyther pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique or priuate. Publique, but yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues, at their ſolemne pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of appointed méetings, where, for their Counter caked Chriſt, againſt the Lorde and his annointed they conſulte and mightly conſpyre, awayting onely
<pb facs="tcp:8972:55"/> theyr trauailing day of ſuch Popiſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. As the laſte good Fridaye in our partes, was a ſuſpected number ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, neare vnto a ſuſpected place, where that horrible ſacrilegious Maſſe, if it often be not, may with greate eaſe, voide of feare, be daily ſacrificed. Their priuate perſuaſions are greate, and wrought by ſundry, ſometime by wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Prieſtes, (harboured of no beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars) ſometyme by popiſhe Phiſitions (greatly magnified of our greater Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes) and theſe ſecreately ſollicite the Romiſhe religion, to men in towne and fieldes, and in their weary beddes, and muche moleſte the valor of the Figge trée.</p>
               <p>But theſe ſinners ſtande the more ſtiffely in their Italienated ſinne, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſtande in that way, whiche manie of oure Worſhipfull and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble States be delighted in: to whiche Popiſhe ſinne all laſhing luſte is fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and their ſtate dothe bréede ſuche ſtoutneſſe, as it is euen at this
<pb facs="tcp:8972:56"/> day déemed a ſin, eyther to reproue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for it, or thys Cancre worme of deathe in them. And can we looke to haue ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Atheiſme, Popery, or Popiſhe hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, once but a little diſgraced, ſo long as the Chaire of aucthority in moſt of our ſhires is filled with the Popiſh ſcorner? Sundry letters are carefully ſent many times to ſearch out Papiſts, but they come to the handes of ſuche, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, as haue more cauſe, to be called themſelues, than to be in commiſſion to conuent others. And what is then done? the packet once receiued, happily there is ſome priuye packing (of the Popiſhe Iuſtice) to thoſe knowne or ſuſpected, ſo as for the tyme, <hi>non est inuentus,</hi> is a good returne: So is God diſhonored, hir Maieſties godly endeuor diſturbed, hir honorable Councell ſet to Schoole, and the poore Figge trée vndigged to hir death. You ſée then of neceſſitie it is, if ye wil (my Lordes whiche haue the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to place into the Chayre of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyce) rightly digge, the hurting matter from the Figge trée:) you muſt take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb facs="tcp:8972:56"/> this earth, that countenaunce and purpoſe whyche earſte haue fedde theſe cancre wormes, I meane that lenitie &amp; mercileſſe pitie, whyche in hope to win thereby the hollow Papiſt, haue great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hurt and hyndered the true hearted Proteſtant. And the verye grounde of your labour, and firſte ſetting the ſpade to the earth, is and muſte here begynne to digge out the Papiſt from the Chaire of auctority: For you may not forgette, that not onely they are fruiteleſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but they make the grounde alſo barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whereſoeuer they rule, yea, they bite at the proſpering Figge trée, they whet the téeth of theyr confederates and are practiſing their purpoſe (vnder the pretence of hir Maieſties power) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the branches, that their cunning maye excell againſte the bodye, and the verye roote of the trée of thys common weale in the day of their decrée. But if that the Atheiſte, hypocriticall and ſcorning Papiſte were altogither diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continued the ſeate of authoritie: No doubt thereof, but their agents the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe
<pb facs="tcp:8972:57"/> practitioners, that ſo conſpire into the heartes of men, againſt Gods truth, durſte not, or could haue ſuch fréedome, neither ſuche ſtanding in ſin, or ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie preuailing aide woulde be lent vnto it. Oh Lorde, worke this yet more effectually, for thy holie names ſake, and for thy loue to the dreſſer of oure Figge trée. And <hi>London, London,</hi> thy Rulers and Gouernours muſte well looke vnto it: For, a little digging in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie dothe driue theſe cancred Papiſtes into thée. So as thou arte become a mother to manye godlye: So alſo, a Nurſe (vnknowen to thée) to manye a wicked Papiſt, whiche breake vp their being in the countrey, and lurke in the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> and ſo are moſte ſafe when they are neareſt the place of their deſerued daunger: as neare to the court, the Councell, the Biſhoppes conſiſtory, <hi>Westminster Hall,</hi> and the ſworde of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. Wherefore my Lord Biſhop muſte be ſtill vigilant, the Iudges di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, the Mayor painefull, all to picke oute the ſcorning Papiſte, thys
<pb facs="tcp:8972:57"/> peſtilent cancre worme, which for more ſafetie, créepeth ſo neare the roote of the Figge trée. The reuerende Fathers muſte bée holpen with the aide of theyr preaching brethren. The godlye Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with the help of their aſſociats. And ſurely (praiſed be God for it) <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> had neuer in mans memory, ſo manye good chriſtian Lawyers, whych with their ſtudy to the Common laws, haue bin ſo able to benefite the bodies in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> common weale, as now they are, by their increaſe in godly knowledge of his holy laws, to furniſh well the Fig trée to hir growth in ſpirite, for the good ſucceſſe to hys church. This the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remaineth (my Lords) that you being our godly Fathers of the law, endeuor with godly ſtrife, to excel one another in digging: and that you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come for your zeale in knowledge, ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and for youre dexteritie in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſo vpright, that al other godly Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſuccéeding you may with reuerent regard, feare to pronounce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentence of Iuſtice after you, leaſte they ſhould not
<pb facs="tcp:8972:58"/> equall your equitie to Papiſt or Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, but chiefly in digging of euil mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the Figge trée. To your god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly furtherance herein, I pray you reade Pſalm. <hi>101.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſeconde worke of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of either eſtate, is to laye to the roote of the Figge trée that which maye ſupple, and comfort, and mightily help the weakened life of the ſame, and is here, by our heauenly dreſſer, exampled vnto ſuche, namely, earneſt and hearty prayer vnto God, to humble his church, to quicken hir, to make ſupple and nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hir veynes, by his ſpirite, that hys ſap may be vigent, and working in hir making hir more &amp; more fruitfull: And then to dung the ſame trée, that is, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicte to it ſuch godly exerciſes, as maye rightly humble theyr heartes, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple their ſoules before God. And that is, the exerciſe of true mourning and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting to the Lorde, approued in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures. Our time dothe aſke it, our ſinnes, his iuſt anger, and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keds glorious bragge dothe enforce it, I
<pb facs="tcp:8972:58"/> meane not, that ordinary courſe of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, whiche the lawes haue whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely enioyned onely, but I pray, in humbleneſſe of my hearte, that to thoſe prouiſions, might be added the purpoſe of the Lorde, in the outward exerciſe of Faſting: That is, that as our plagues are to be feared greatelye, bycauſe oure liues are ſo far oute of order, our mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and faſting ſhoulde be ſuche, as might be extraordinary, &amp; yet not voide of Gods ordinaunce, and may be ſayde to conſiſt in theſe two branches: Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the outwarde exerciſe of abſtine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and in the inwarde drawing of water. The outward exerciſe of true faſting to humble and ſupple the hearte, the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture commendeth vnto vs thus: Firſte, that we by aucthoritie, I ſay, by auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Paſtor, and Magiſtrate,<note place="margin">Zoph. 2.1. Ioel 1 &amp;. 2. Ionas. 3.7. Nehem, 9.1 1. Sam. 7 3. Ezra. 8.21.</note> bée aſſembled into the houſe of God, there to doe theſe thinges, for, and during the whole daye, whyche oughte to bée as a Sabbaoth vnto vs. Firſt the Miniſters (Gods Prophetes) are to preache to vs the lawe of GOD, and to ſignifie
<pb facs="tcp:8972:59"/> our tranſgreſſions vnto God, againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, which then ſhal moſt humble vs, when of purpoſe wée aſſemble to that end: (and herof reade we in <hi>Ieremy. 36.6.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere. 36.6</note> and the whole Chapiter: In <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> the eight and ninth Chapiter, to the diligent reading whereof, at thy comming home, I beſéeche thée good people.) Whoſe Sermons, muſt be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured to ſhewe the cauſe of oure aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, and to lay open, Gods anger againſte vs, and the imminent daunger that hangeth ouer vs, whyche can not but proue the heartes of euerye ſuche, as haue any life of Gods ſpirite in them, thoughe by our inſolencie, abuſing hys greate patience, the ſame lye as almoſte dead within vs. And further, the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers office in thys faſting daye, is, to pray God hartily for the people. <hi>1. Sam. 7.4. Ioel. 2.17.</hi> Their direction to the people is ruled to vs thus. That they in that day of faſte, ſhould not only ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly for euer after, vtterly deteſte all ſin &amp; iniquitie, but that they alſo obſtain fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> things otherwiſe approued lawfull,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:59"/> and requiſite, yea, very neceſſarye. And theſe maye bée thus diuided: Into the godly abſtinence of the Chriſtian faſter, from lawful and godly pleaſures: And into the like abſtinence from neceſſarye ſuſtenaunce. <hi>Let the Bridegroome goe out of his chamber, and the Bride forth of hir cloſet</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>Ioel. 2.16. Let ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and beaſt put on ſackcloth, ſaith the lawe of Niniuie, Ionah, 3.8.</hi> which law, though it ſtrictly tye not vs, yet ought Chriſtians to conſider, howe abſurde a thing it is, and farre from the Analogie, of a true humbled ſpirite, in the day of faſt to aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble with the church in prowde, ſhining, and glorious appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel: for nothing may be the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and there ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, whiche doth not moue to mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. And for that our labour &amp; trade of occupatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; merchandize, worketh profit &amp; ſo pleaſure, &amp; the vſe of it that day, doth work impediment to our faſt, therfore,<note place="margin">Daniel. 9.5.</note> the day of Gods faſt we muſt ſolemnize as a Sabbaoth to the LORD, as to the Iewes it was commanded,<note place="margin">Leu. 17.26.30.31 32. ch. ch 23.7.8.</note> and as a chriſtian help, to our humilitie, before
<pb facs="tcp:8972:60"/> the Lord, is yet by aucthoritie to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, as the Lorde ſhall worke them, to thinke it conuenient. The holy abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from meates,<note place="margin">Eſther. 4.16 Ionah. 3.7.</note> is alſo in our godly faſte required, not that thereby, God is ſimply pleaſed, but that thereby, our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhoulde be leſſe ſturdy, and our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites more humbled and apt to praye.</p>
               <p>And this is the very cauſe why abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from (not one kinde of meate, as fleſhe onely, but from) all ſorts of ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, is in the Scriptures ſo ofte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, namely, that neither fulneſſe ſhoulde make vs luſtye and proude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte oure God, or drowſie and ſlée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, when we were to heare of our ſin: but that oure hungrye bodyes, myghte teache our pyned ſoules, what néed wée haue to crye for the foode of life, and how vnable to liue wythout his hand, whom we ſo mightily offende, and that the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting worme of hunger, mighte helpe to tame, and bring obedient to the ſpirite, that fleſhe, whiche farced full, hathe ſo contemned, to ſtoupe vnto his God. Lo, this is the true vſe of oure abſtinence,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:60"/> from all meates in Gods holye faſting daye. But to abſtaine from meates, by choice, and to vſe other, for religion, is méerely euil and Diabolicall. <hi>1. Tim. 4.</hi> Againe, to abſtaine from meates, and not to vſe the inward exerciſe, is to prophane the holy right of faſting vnto God, <hi>Eſay. 58.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Wherefore, lette vs conſider the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of true faſting vnto the Lord, according to his worde. This dothe conſiſte, as we haue ſaide, in the inward drawing of water, and is ſet forth to vs by <hi>Samuel</hi> at <hi>Mizpeh,</hi> when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord had returned the Arke, &amp; increaſed the zeale to right religion, in his people, whyche twenty yeares and more had bin retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the <hi>Philistines. <hi>Samuel</hi>
                  </hi> ſayd,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 7.1.</note> 
                  <hi>If yee bee truely turned to the Lord, and come to him with youre heartes, then putte away the ſtraunge Gods from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt you, and <hi>Aſhtaroth,</hi> and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte your heartes vnto the Lorde, and ſerue him onely, and hee ſhall delyuer you out of the hands of the <hi>Philistines.</hi>
                  </hi> Then the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did putte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb facs="tcp:8972:61"/> 
                  <hi>Baalim</hi> and <hi>Aſhtaroth</hi> and ſerued the Lorde onelye. And <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaide: <hi>Gather al <hi>Iſrael</hi> togither at <hi>Mizpeh,</hi> &amp; I wil pray for you, and they gathered togither to <hi>Mizpeh,</hi> and drew water, and powred it out, before the Lord, &amp; faſted the ſame day, and ſaid there: We haue ſinned agaynſte the Lorde, &amp;c.</hi> Thys tyme aunſwereth ours, and here after oure twentye yeares and odde, of Gods mercifull returne to vs, what dothe he aſke of vs, but that wée, if wée be come to him with our hearts, put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Popiſh Chriſte, and that <hi>Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taroth,</hi> that Italian God and Romiſhe Prieſt the Pope, and his pelfe?</p>
               <p>And ſecondelye, that we directe oure heartes, not to our mincing, but to hys Maieſtie, and ſerue him onely, and not oure carnall pollicie, that we faſte and pray, and draw water, and powre it out before the Lorde. That is, that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our ſinnes, reproued by his worde, and hauing our bodies, broughte vnder in abſtinence, our ſpirites humbled, at
<pb facs="tcp:8972:61"/> the ſighte of oure ſinnes, wée ſhoulde wyth Chriſtian compunction, digge the ſtonye fountaine of our hearts, and wyth <hi>Dauid, Daniel, Peter, Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene,</hi> and the Sainctes of God drawe thence the ſalted water of the ſame, and plentifullye poure it forthe, by the conducte of the eye, and that, before the Lorde, not before Sathan, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughe diſpaire, with <hi>Iudas</hi> or <hi>Achy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel,</hi> or hypocriticallye before men, wyth <hi>Achab</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. K. 21 27. Iere. 41.1.6</note> purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing no amendment, but after miſchief: but ſimply before the Lorde, with theſe Iſraelites and godly <hi>Samuel</hi> in <hi>Miz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peh,</hi> and vnfainedly cry, and confeſſe to his Maieſtie and fatherly mercie: Wée haue ſinned Lorde and done vniuſtlye: We haue neglected the glorie of thy Arke and Teſtamente: We haue loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed oure heauenly <hi>Mannah,</hi> thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed worde: Wée haue lefte oure firſt loue, and become barren Figge trées. Wherefore, thy wrath is kindled, and thy fury is waxen hote.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8972:62"/>
               <p>But behold, we thus embrace thy ſon, our ſauiour Chriſt, and proſtrate oure ſelues before thée: We caſte from oure ſelues, all ſuperſtition, and that ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Prieſt, thy great enimy: Wée humble our ſelues in thys thine appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued exerciſe: We offer our ſelues by our onely ſacrificing Prieſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> Chriſte Ieſus, vnto thée, a holy turned people, and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offering, whych is our reaſonable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of thée: We therefore efteſoones be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thée to ſpare vs, at our only media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor God &amp; man, Ieſus, our dreſſers peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ceaſe thy ready ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: <hi>Cut them downe.</hi> As theſe laws for faſting, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hir Maieſtie hathe godlily giuen vs, be good: So let vs pray God, that thys our like addition, by hir gracious aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie maye be added, and ſo ſhall the Fig trée, haue rightly, his moſte fertile compoſe, Amen Lord Ieſu. But let vs knowe, that neyther <hi>Samuel</hi> can profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably pray, or the people rightly &amp; plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully drawe water, and faſte to pleaſe GOD, excepte they turne in heart to God.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8972:62"/>
               <p>And further note of <hi>Samuels</hi> wordes, that the duty of true conuerſion, is, firſt to caſte out of the Chayre and Churche, <hi>Baalym</hi> and <hi>Aſhtaroth,</hi> the Italian Prieſt and his adherents, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our heartes vnto the Lorde, in the right addreſſing to his faſte, whych ſhal bring vndoubtedly his olde aduaile, to oure preſent Figge trée, that is, though, when we be beſte diſpoſed at <hi>Mizpeh,</hi> the <hi>Philistines</hi> take occaſion to work our ſpoile (ſome by fawning flatterye, and ſome by open warre) yet the Lord will rowſe vppe hys ſtrength for vs, and hée wil aſſemble the chariots of his Angels, and the artillerie of hys thunderclappes (if men were not of force by him) to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe the confederates againſte vs, that with eaſie purſute we ſhall ouerthrowe all Popiſhe <hi>Philistines:</hi> As, to our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable example and doctrine, we may reade the Lorde to haue done, for theſe his beloued in <hi>Mizpeh, <hi>1. Sam. 7.7.</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And finally our kingdome, by hys mighty hand, ſhal be then preſerued, hir Maieſtie in much godlyneſſe, long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued,
<pb facs="tcp:8972:63"/> and we, hir faithful ſubiects, ſhal henceforth liue in al godly peace, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God. This, &amp; al other thy graces, we beſéech thée (o Lord) to grant in thy great &amp; rich mercy, to hir maieſtie thy ſeruante, hir counſel, to al ſpirituall paſtors, Magiſtrats &amp; people, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole realme of <hi>Englande,</hi> and hir Graces do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, that we may not be cut down as barren Figge trées, but maye endure bleſſed, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Palme trée, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riuers ſide planted, &amp; euery of vs, to bring forth our allotted fruites. in due ſeaſon, in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Faith, by the meaſure of true Charitie, in the garden of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, through Chriſt our Lorde, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, togither with thée (O deare Father) and the holy Ghoſt, thrée diſtinct perſons, and one eternall God, be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, glorie, power, and dominion, for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Laudes Deo per Chriſtum ſeruatorem noſtrum.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:8972:63"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
